<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Several petitions answered, that were put up by the priests of Westmorland, against James Nayler and Geo. Fox, servants of the most high God, persecuted by the priests of the world, as Jesus Christ and the apostles were persecuted by the Jewish high priests for the witnessing of the truth, and testifying against the deceits of the world. With the answer to an order given forth by the justices at Appleby sessions, contrary to the law of God, and the laws of the land. Also, an exhortation to the people, to mind the light of God in them, the teachings and leadings of the spirit of truth; the which if it be obeyed, will lead and guide them into all truth.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89853</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N316A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E703_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872441</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872441</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89853)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E703[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Several petitions answered, that were put up by the priests of Westmorland, against James Nayler and Geo. Fox, servants of the most high God, persecuted by the priests of the world, as Jesus Christ and the apostles were persecuted by the Jewish high priests for the witnessing of the truth, and testifying against the deceits of the world. With the answer to an order given forth by the justices at Appleby sessions, contrary to the law of God, and the laws of the land. Also, an exhortation to the people, to mind the light of God in them, the teachings and leadings of the spirit of truth; the which if it be obeyed, will lead and guide them into all truth.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black spread Eagle at the West end of Paulsl.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to James Nayler. cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Includes texts of the petitions.</note>
                  <note>"An epistle to the reader" signed: Richard Farnworth.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 29 1653".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:124878:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
SEVERAL PETITIONS ANSWERED, That were put up by the Prieſts of WESTMORLAND, Againſt <hi>James Nayler</hi> and <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> Servants of the moſt High God, perſecuted by the Prieſts of the world, as Jeſus Chriſt and the Apoſtles were perſecuted by the Jewiſh high Prieſts for the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing of the truth, and teſtifying againſt the deceits of the world.</p>
            <p>With the anſwer to an Order given forth by the juſtices at <hi>Appleby</hi> Seſſions, contrary to the Law of God, and the Laws of the Land.</p>
            <p>Alſo, an exhortation to the people, to mind the light of God in them, the teachings and leadings of the Spirit of Truth; the which if it be obeyed, will lead and guide them into all truth.</p>
            <q>This is the condemnation, That light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evill: He that loves the light brings his deeds to the light, that the light may prove them; but he that doth evill hateth the light, neither cometh he to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved. But he that loveth the truth, and doth that which is righteous, cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt, that they are wrought in God, <bibl>
                  <hi>John 3. 19, 20, 21</hi> verſes.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Little Children, let no man deceive you, he that doth righteouſneſs is righteous, even as he is righteous; he that committeth ſin, is of the Divell: In this the children of God are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and the children of the Divel, whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God, neither he that loveth not his brother, <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Iohn 7, 8, 9, 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Marvell not if the world hate you, it hated me before it hated you, <bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Bleſſed are you when men ſhall hate you and when they ſhall ſeparate you from their company, and ſhall reproach you, and caſt out your name as evill, for the Son of Mans ſake, rejoyce ye in that day, and leap for joy, for behold, great is your reward in heaven, for in the like manner did their fathers unto the Prophets, <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 6. 22, 23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black ſpread Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:124878:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:124878:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Emember the words of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who ſaid, the ſervant was not greater then his Lord, and ſaith he, if they have perſecuted me, they will perſecute you alſo; and ſaith he marvell not if the world hate you, it hated me before it hated you, if ye were of the world the world would love you, but becauſe I have choſen you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you, but theſe are the fruits of darkneſs, that ariſeth from <hi>Cains</hi> genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they that are after the fleſh, t ey perſecute them that are after the Spirit, it is the world that perſecutes, and as they are in their naturall ſtate and condition, they know not God, but are enemies both to him, and His, where he is made manifeſt in Spirit; they that are in the corrupt nature are ignorant of him, according as it is written in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the naturall man knowes not the things of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned, and no man knowes the Father but the Son, neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any man the Son but the Father and he to whom the Son reveals him; there is no knowing of God, but by the Revelation of his Spirit: but naturall men ſuch as the
<pb facs="tcp:124878:3"/>
Prieſts of the world who are ignorant of God and are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to him, being guided by the ſpirit of error, ſtanding up in actuall Rebellion againſt God, now that he is Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Son in the hearts of his people, and leading them by the Divine light of his holy Spirit out of Egypt, out of bondage and darkneſs wherein they have been held in the time of the fall, while the myſtery of iniquitie hath been working, and Antichriſt ſitting in the Temple of God, as God, ſhewing himſelf to be God, and the Prieſts of the world have been caſting a miſt before the eyes of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the people by their Greek, Latin, and Hebrew, which is but dung, and droſſe, earthie, and ayrie, hath driven the people into earthly conceivings &amp; imagination, having no other knowledge of God but by conceiving and imagining of him, &amp; are of thoſe whom the Lord complains of by his ſervant the Prophet ſaying, This people draweth near me with their mouth, and with their lips do they honor me, but their hearts is far from me, and their fear towards me is taught by the precepts of men, therefore thus ſaith the Lord, I will gather thoſe that have been ſcattered in the Cloudie and dark day, and I will teach them my ſelf, and write my Law in their hearts, and put my Spirit in their inward parts; then ſhall ye know that I the Lord have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it, and I will take you from among the hearthen, and gather you out of all Countries, and ſprinkle clear water upon you, and cleanſe you from all your uncleanneſs: a new heart alſo will I give you, and a new Spirit will I put with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, and I will cauſe you to walk in my ſtatutes to do them, <hi>Ezek. 36.</hi> Chapter. Now the Lord is fulfilling his Promiſes made of old to the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> after the ſpirit the Immortall ſeed that is begotten not by the will of man but by the will of God, and born again of water and the ſpirit, being ſeparated from all uncleanneſs, and they that live in the filth of the fleſh, fulfilling the luſts
<pb facs="tcp:124878:3"/>
thereof know them not that are born again, waſhed and cleanſed, ſanctified and justified, and are taught of God and made pertakers of the Divine nature, but are enemies to them, it is the ſame generation now that perſecuts, that perſecuted from the beginning, but it is but that the Scriptures may be fulfilled, the Beaſt ſhall make War with the Saints, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> joyns together in Battle againſt the Lamb, the Priests of the world are the greateſt perſecutors of the truth of God. Now as the High Prieſt was when Jeſus Chriſt came in the fleſh, the chief Priests were the greateſt perſecutors of him then, ſtirring up the Rulers, and Elders, and the rude multitude againſt him, calling him A deceiver and A blaſphemer and they ſpued forth their envie againſt him in raiſing falſe witneſſes againſt him, and every way incenſing the People againſt him to cry out to have him put to death, <hi>Saying, Crucifie him, Crucifie him, and let us have Barabbas let looſe which was a murderer,</hi> and if thou do but Read this little enſuing treatiſe thou ſhalt finde ſomething worthy of thy labour being ſingle eyed, thou wilt be brought to ſee Antichriſt or the man of ſin in A high meaſure, the myſtery of iniquitie acting in the Prieſts of the world, that do profeſſe themſelves to be the Miniſters of Chriſt, but are of the Synagogue of Satan, and are enemies to Jeſus Chriſt where he is made manifeſt and raiſed up in the ſpirits of any to teſtifie againſt their deceits wherein they do deceive the people, and are in the ſame ſtate and condition that the Jewiſh High Prieſts were in, that put Chriſt to death: as thou readeſt keep thy eye ſingle and be not Partiall, and thou ſhalt ſee that the battell is begun betwixt <hi>Michael</hi> and the Dragon, &amp; the Dragon he caſteth forth floods of revil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and reproaches, and perſecutions after the man childe Chriſt Jeſus as he is ariſing in the ſpirits of his people, to
<pb facs="tcp:124878:4"/>
ſtifle him in the birth that he may not come forth to raign, and where he is Born up into the underſtandings of any ruling by the Divine Power of his Spirit in any, the Dragon with his ſeven golden heads, or the Prieſts under ſever all Colours being the painted Beaſt that is gilded with their glorious notions, having painted themſelves over with the words of the Prophets and Apoſtles, that ſuffered by ſuch as they are of the ſame generation, whoſe heart is deceitfull and that above meaſure, being full of ſubtiltie, the Serpents head being unbruiſed in them, they labour every way as the Jewiſh High Prieſts did, to deſtroy thoſe who are brought to walk in the ſame ſtate and condition that the holy men of God did. In former ages, men that were blameleſs and harmleſs in their lives and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were guided by the holy ſpirit of God that ruleth in them, I know it by experience, being acquainted with them in their godly converſation, which thoſe Cainiſh and Jewiſh ſpirited Prieſts goes about to caſt dirt upon, making them odious to the world ſtirring up the people in envie and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licionſneſs againſt them, if it were poſsible to take away their lives, and the Jewiſh high Prieſts ſtirred up the rulers and Elders of the people againſt both Jeſus Chriſt and the Apostles who were his true Ministers, to perſecute, Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and put them to death, ſo do theſe stir up not onely the rude people in envie and malice, but they ſtir up the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Rulers of the people by their falſe petitions to incenſe them againſt a harmleſs and an innocent people to take away if not their lives, yet their liberties, but where the Lord doth appear in any of the Rulers of the people they will ſee into the wickedneſs of the Prieſts that they are thoſe that perſecute the Lord of life in his Saints and ſervants, and they do openly manifeſt themſelves that they are none of the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, for they
<pb facs="tcp:124878:4"/>
did never perſecute nor impriſon, but on the contrary were both perſecuted and impriſoned, and ſo are thoſe to whom Jeſus Chriſt is made manifeſt in ſpirit, now the Lord is ſetting up the Kingdom of his Son in the ſpirits of his people, and the Kingdom of Antichriſt, Babylon, the myſtery of iniquity must be thrown down: take heed of holding up that which God will not have to stand, he is ſetting up the miniſtery of his Son in the ſpirits of his People, and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down the miniſtery of Antichriſt, which is the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry of the world, as it is made manifest hey do openly appear to thoſe that have their eyes in their head. Now friend if thou do but read this with thy underſtanding thou ſhalt ſee that theſe perſecuting Priests knowes nothing of God but are enemies to him, and are guided by the Spirit of error walking contrary to Christ and his Apostles, who were his true miniſters and were guided by his holy Spirit, and ſuffered by the miniſtry of the word, as thoſe dear hearts do that are guided I am ſure by the Spirit of the Lord: and are as dear to him as the Apple of his eye, and if thou do but give thy diligence in reading to Read by the ſame guide that thoſe are led by that write the enſuing treatiſe, it will bring thee to ſee the innocency and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their blomeles lives and converſation that they are made to ſuffer willingly for Righteouſnes ſake according to the command of Jeſus Chriſt and walkers in his obedience, knowing that their reward is in Heaven, having their converſation in Heaven according to that of the Apoſtle in the third to the <hi>Philip. 20.</hi> And their affections being ſet on things above and not on the earth ſeeking a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom but not of this world, for were they of this world, the world would love its own, but becauſe they are choſen out of the worlds ways and worſhips, cuſtomes and faſhions, being dead with Chriſt from the rudiments of the world,
<pb facs="tcp:124878:5"/>
are brought to worſhip God in ſpirit being born again of water and the Spirit as <hi>John 3.</hi> and having their ſouls purified in yielaing abedience to the commands of the Spirit as the Saints had which more obedient to the ſame ſpirit, which purified their ſouls, as in <hi>1 Pet. 1. 22, 23.</hi> Who were born again as theſe are, Children of the moſt High God whom the world and the perſecuting envious Frieſts know not; for the ſpirit that is in them, is not of God. becauſe it Iuſteth to envy bontrary to the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt, which is pure and holy, and is loving, as it is raiſed up in any to rule and guide them, it beareth all the worlds Judgements, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, Revilings, and Perſecutions, and ſuffereth with Joy, having the promiſe of this life, and that which is to come, thus ſaith the Lord, woe to the wicked it ſhall be ill with them, and they ſhall be rewarded according to their doings as in Iſaiah the 3. 10. But ſay unto the righteous it ſhall be well with them, v. 11. and ſaith Jeſus Chriſt bleſſed are you when men revile you, and perſecute you and ſay all manner of evil againſt you falfly, as the Prieſts do by thoſe innocent and harmleſs ones who are dear and precious in the ſight of God, and may rejoyce, for their reward is great in Heaven, according to that of our Saviour in <hi>Mat. 5. 10. 11. 12.</hi> And that of <hi>Peter:</hi> who ſaith if ye be reproached for the name of Chriſt happy are you, for the ſpirit of grace and of glory Reſteth on you, Rejoyce and be exceeding glad: all ye that love the Lord, Bleſſe ye the Lord, praiſe him and magnifie him for ever, for the Lord is glorifying himſelf and making his power known, and all the Crowns, of pride and vain glory, and fleſhly exaltation muſt be thrown down, and the Son of his Love Raiſed up and exalted in the hearts of his people to ſit upon his Throne, Rejoyce for evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A Friend to the Truth of God, where it is made manifeſt.
Richard Farnworth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124878:5"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>To the Right Worſhipfull the Juſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>WESTMORLAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of divers Ministers and other Inhabitants in the ſaid County who earneſtly deſire the Glory of God, and the Peace of his Church, and this Common-Wealth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Humbly Sheweth,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat <hi>James Nayler,</hi> and <hi>George Fox,</hi> men whoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, habitation, profeſſion, and condition, is to us generally unknown, meerly of their own accord, without any Paſport, Licence, or Authority what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, that they can ſhew, or we ever heard of, have entered in to the County, and together with ſome others their companions and Proſelytes, who are riſen up among our ſelves in it, have filled it in ſome parts with very ſad diviſions and diſtractions, ſtirred up much hatred, wrath, and ſtrife, even between the neareſt relations; and powerfully ſeduced multitudes of People from the Truth, and true worſhip of God, to imbrace their own corrupt and dangerous Doctrines, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their pernicions wayes; which things are ſo notoriouſly known to all men, that live in theſe parts, that we need not here ſay any thing to acquaint your ſelves with it.</p>
               <p>And though theſe men tell people where they come, that they are ſent to them from God, to declare what he hath revealed in them, and labour to perſwade them that they come to them with the Authority of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:124878:6"/>
the Apoſtles of Chriſt, yet our ſelves do confidently believe and know them to be wicked men, deceivers, and the very Miniſters of Satan, as may appear,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By the Horrid Blaſphemies which they have uttered.</item>
                  <item>2. By the damnable Hereſies and dangerous Errors which they have avouched.</item>
               </list>
               <p>All which they tend not onely to the diſturbance of the publique Peace, and ſafety of the Common wealth, but to the ſubverſion of all Government, we do in all Humility addreſſe our ſelves,</p>
               <p>Humbly and earneſtly praying, as you tender the Glory of God, and the good of ſo many ſouls as are or may be iudangered by their impious principles and practices, that you would be pleaſed to make uſe of that Authority where with the Lord hath Inveſted you, ſpeedily to provide for the ſafety of true Religion and the publique Peace, by checking the wicked endeavours, and proceedings of theſe men, which we humbly conceive may be at leaſt by ordering <hi>James Nayler,</hi> and <hi>George Fox,</hi> &amp;c. being ſtrangers to depart out of this County, and to return to their own homes. <hi>Francis Howgill</hi> to be of better deportment, ſpecially to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Magiſtracie and Miniſtry of <hi>England,</hi> And by enjoyning <hi>John Ayrey, Alexander Dixon,</hi> and the reſt of the ſpeakers and followers that live in this County, to abide at their own Homes, ſtudy to be quiet, and do their own buſineſs, labouring in their own calling, which is the Apoſtles rule, and not to wander up and down the Country, as Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, to draw Diſciples after them, ſave only in a way of Travell as private men about their own occaſions; and the Lords Gracious guidance of your ſelves in the affairs of ſo great concernment, we ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This is a true Coppie of the pretended Miniſters and profeſſors in this County given up at the Court at laſt Seſſions at <hi>Appleby.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="responses">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:124878:6"/>
               <head>Severall Petitions anſwered, that were put up by the Prieſts of <hi>WESTMORLAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="response">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſt.</hi> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the Right Worſhipfull the Juſtices of the peace for the County of <hi>Westmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Them that are right, deny <note place="margin">Acts 19. 27. John 5. 44. John 4. 22. Prov. 20. 3. Rev. 14. 7.</note> all worſhips, and worſhip God, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the Lord, <hi>All honour and glory be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto the Lord.</hi> Now Man where is thy honour? Yet I honour all men in the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſt. Obj.</hi> The humble Petition of divers Miniſters, and other inhabitants in the ſaid County, who earneſtly deſire the glory of God, and the peace of his Church, and this Commonwealth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Miniſters of God never put up a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Gal. r. 1. John 18. 35.</note> to an outward Magiſtrate to maintain the Church of God. Here you ſhew your Miniſtery is of man, and muſt be upheld by an earthly power: and here you ſhew that Church is carnal, and muſt be maintained by a carnall weapon, as the Jews did, which came againſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124878:7"/>
                     <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſaid he was <hi>a peſtilent fellow,</hi> who did witneſs <note place="margin">Acts 24. 5. Acts 17. 6. Col. 2. 17.</note> forth the ſubſtance, Jeſus Chriſt, of all theſe types and figures which the Jewes lived in, therefore his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine did overturn them, to the letting forth of the <note place="margin">Gal. 3 13. 1 Pet. 3. 19.</note> ſeed: for that Mind that held up the Figure, did not own the ſubſtance Jeſus Chriſt, when he was come. Now all you pretended Miniſters of Chriſt, Jeſus <note place="margin">2 Tim 3. 5. Mark 3. 22.</note> Chriſt is come and made manifeſt in his Saints; you who have the form deny him, and the power, and ſome call it witchery, ſome of the Divell; but that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can do no other, for it is the ſame naure that was in the Jewes, who would maintain their way, and hold up their cuſtomes, and perſecute him that was the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and called him Divell: But the Church Jeſus Chriſt is the head of, and the Church is the pillar and <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 15. Col 1. 24. Rev. 5. 9.</note> ground of truth, and Chriſt hath redeemed his Church with his blood, and who are redeemed by the pretious blood of Ieſus Chriſt, are of the Church, and them I do witneſs, and not one of them ſhall be plucked out of <note place="margin">John 10. 29.</note> his hand, whom the Father hath given me, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 10. 28, 29, 30, 31 My Father which gave me them is greater then all, and no man is able to pluck them <note place="margin">John 18. 36.</note> out of my Fathers hands. I and my Father are one. Then the Iews took up ſtones to ſtone him, Chriſt hath no carnal weapon to maintain his Church, for his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not of this world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Obj.</hi> Humbly ſheweth, that <hi>James Nayler</hi> and <hi>George Fox,</hi> men whoſe countrey, habitation, profeſſion and condition is to us generally unknown.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, our habitation is with the Lord, and our Countrey is not of this world, neither are our conditions known unto the world; for who had the power of truth was never known unto the world, where
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124878:7"/>
the ſame power is made manifeſt, 'tis ſo now, the world <note place="margin">John 15 19, 20 Heb. 11. 14, 15, 16. John 15. 18.</note> knows them not, therefore they hate you, and perſecute you, the Scripture's here fulfilled, As they have done unto me, ſo will they do unto you, ſaith Chriſt. Here the Scripture is fulfilled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Obj.</hi> Merely of their own accord, without any paſport, or licenſe, or authority that they can ſhew, or we ever heard of, entred into the County, and together with ſome others their companions and proſelites riſen up among our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Miniſters of God never were ſent forth <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 24. Gal. 1. 1. Jer. 23. 31, 32.</note> by the authority of man: Here you ſhew your ſelves to be blind guides indeed, <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle, not of man, nor by man, but by Ieſus Chriſt; neither was the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel he preached, according to man: and this do we witneſs, that our authority is not from man, neither our call from man; for he that ſpeaks of himſelf ſpeaks a lie; and all you who ſpeak, &amp; not from the mouth of the Lord, are falſ Prophets, and there you ſhew your ſelves to be no Prophets of the Lord, no Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; for if you were the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and had not received it of man, nor your Goſpel according to man, then would ye witneſs us; for that which we preach, is not after man, neither according to mans will, but by the will of God: For we are not made Miniſters by <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> for that we deny. <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 21, 12. Gal. 1. 1.</note> We ſtand condemned by you who are Miniſters of the Letter, and not of the Spirit, who are Miniſters by the will of man, and your Call and Authority is by the will of man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> Hvae filled it in ſome parts with very ſad di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truth did make diviſion when Deceit was at
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124878:8"/>
peace: For Chriſt ſaid, I come not to ſend peace on the <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 34, 35</note> earth, but a ſword, for I am come to ſet a man at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance againſt his Father, and the daughter againſt her mother, the daughter in law againſt the mother in law, and here is the Scripture fulfilled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Obj.</hi> Stirred up much wrath and ſtrife, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the neereſt relation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It ſeems hatred, wrath and ſtrife were within, now truth hath ſtirred it up. When the ſtrong man ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med keeps the houſe, all the goods are at peace, till a <note place="margin">Mat 3. 27. Luke 17. 20, 21.</note> ſtronger come and diſpoſſeſſes him and ſpoyls his goods: and here is the Scripture fulfilled, where the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 19. 1 John 3. 8.</note> power of truth dwels, and the Kingdom of God is come, who are indeed the Temples of God; the works of the Divell deſtroyed, hatred, malice, wrath, ſtrife, hereſie and blaſphemy, pride, hypocriſie and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, where the truth rules, theſe are deſtroyed; and where theſe rule truth rules not, and conſider all you pretended Miniſters what you have been doing all this while, that there is ſo much wrath and ſtrife to be ſtirred up, when the truth comes, for that is it that ſets at variance. O all people conſider what blind guides you have been led withall, why ſpend you your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which ſatisfieth not? Ho every one that thirſteth, <note place="margin">Iſai. 55. 1, 2, 3.</note> come freely, without mony and without price, hearken diligently unto me ſaith the Lord, that your ſouls may live.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Obj.</hi> And powerfully ſeduced multitudes of people from the truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whereas we are accuſed, as ſeducing people from the truth, it is falſe: for how can they be in the truth who live in malice, cnvy, ſtrife, and wrath? for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124878:8"/>
they that live in that nature are turned from the truth; which according to your own words much of that is <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 9. Col. 2. 22. 1 John 2. 26, 27.</note> ſtirred up. The Lord hath ſent us, and made us to come into this County, to draw up people unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, from the Doctrines and Worſhips of the world. <note place="margin">John 11 7.</note> All people are ſeduced by you whom God hath never ſent; for I will prove by the Scriptures that you are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, and draw people from the teaching within them, to follow your imaginations, what you can ſtudy out of the letter which the holy men of God ſpoke forth freely, the which now you make a Trade of. And <hi>Iohn</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 26, 27.</note> ſaid, Theſe things have I written unto you concerning them that ſeduce you, you need not that any man teach you, but as the anointing teaches you all things. Now if an hundred, or a thouſand people ſhould come and deny all you Prieſts, and witneſs they had this anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting within them; then this Scripture being fulfilled, <note place="margin">John 15. 25.</note> and you denied, ſuch you go about to perſecute which witneſs this anointing within them, and need no man teach them. Herein you ſhew that you have not the ſame ſpirit that was in them that wrot that Epiſtle, but the ſpirit of the world; the world did not know them then, which were taught by that anointing, but hated them, as you do now, them that witneſs the ſame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing ye hate; ye are the Antichriſts of this world, and hate them who are not of this world, and ſeek to bring them from their teacher within, to follow you who go in the way of <hi>Cain</hi> to envy, and after the error <note place="margin">Jude 11.</note> of <hi>Balaam.</hi> Here you ſhew your ſelves to be ſeducers, and ſuch we do deny, but to every mans conſcience do we look to be made manifeſt; and we do not ſeek to draw any one from the anointing within them, but do exhort all there to wait and abide for the promiſe,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124878:9"/>
which is eternall life to them that abide in the anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 2. 1 John 2. 25. 2 Tim. 3. 3.</note> but you falſe accuſers are without, which the Scripture ſpeaks of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Ob.</hi> And from the worſhip of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is falſe, to ſay we draw any from the truth; for we can do nothing againſt the truth, but for the truth, as the Apoſtle ſaith: but all corrupt wayes we deny and abhorre, and the worſhip of the wicked we deny, who have not their names written in the Lambs Book of life, and God is not worſhipped with mens hands, neither dwels he in Temples made with hands; and for witneſſing this, <hi>Steven</hi> was ſtoned to death when the high Prieſts examined him; which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration you ſhew your ſelves to be, in the ſame nature, holding up outward Temples and Synagogues, which we deny, and ſeek to draw people from theſe things. God is a Spirit, and he that worſhips him muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in ſpirit and in truth, and this worſhip we own, <note place="margin">Rev. 13. 8. Ioh. 4. 22, 25. Acts 19. 27, 24</note> and draw people to it up to God from all beaſtly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, outward Cuſtomes imitated of man, which is an abomination unto the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Ob.</hi> To imbrace their corrupt and dangerous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and pernitions ways; which things are ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly known to all men that live in theſe parts, that we need not here ſay any thing to acquaint your ſelves with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Corrupt Doctrines &amp; pernicious ways we deny, which are all your ways you proud <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, for <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 2. 15. 2 John 1. 9. Luke 7. 9.</note> he that doth abide in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath God, and he that doth not abide in the Doctrine of Chriſt, is of the Divell: Ieſus Chriſt is made manifeſt, who witneſſes forth the eternall truth to poor ſouls, who have lived in darkneſs and blindneſs theſe many
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124878:9"/>
hundred years have the dark miniſtery reigned, but now the God of power is uttering his thunders, and <note place="margin">Rev. 10. 34.</note> making his power known, and the eternal word of God is made manifeſt in us, this we witneſs, which we preach forth, to the glory of our Father, Praiſes, praiſes be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee alone Lord God Almighty, who art now ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up thy own Kingdom. And the ſame judgement do ye give upon us as the Jews did upon Chriſt and the Apoſtles; for the Apoſtle while he was in the Jewiſh Religion, in their outward worſhip, as you are now, they looking for a Chriſt coming without them, as you do now (at which time) <hi>Paul</hi> was at peace with them; but when he did preach Ieſus Chriſt that was revealed <note place="margin">Acts 21. 27, 28, 30.</note> in him, then they haled him out of the Temple, and perſecuted him, &amp; could not own nor beleeve what was revealed in him: ſo if any ſhould come amongſt you now, and tell you that God dwels not in Temples made <note place="margin">Acts 17. 24, 25.</note> with hands, neither was he worſhipped with mens hands, ye would hate them, beat them, or ſtone them, as they did the Apoſtles. This ye do that the Scripture might be fulfilled, The time ſhall come, when they ſhal <note place="margin">John 16. 2.</note> put you out of their Synagogues, and ſhall hale you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Magiſtrates, and who ſhall kill you will think he doth God good ſervice: And do not you ſhew your ſelves openly to be of this generation? Will you have another meaning for the Scriptures? There are but two ways, the one is pure and leads up to the Father; the other ſtands pretending God and Chriſt, which way you are in, perſecuting us who poſſes the truth. Here's <note place="margin">John 8. 41, 33. Luke 13. 24.</note> the ſtand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Ob.</hi> And though theſe people, tell people where they come, that they are ſent to them from God to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what he hath revealed in them, and labour to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124878:10"/>
perſwade them that they come to them with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Chriſt and of the Apoſtles, yet our ſelves do confidently beleeve and know them to be wicked men, deceivers and the very Miniſters of Satan, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our call we witneſs is of the Lord, not by man, that makes you whoſe call is by man ſo perſecute <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 33. 34. Gal. 1. 1. 1 Cor. 1. 26. 27. 28.</note> us; your own will is ſtanding, you rage againſt any that come contrary to the will of man, if ever you witneſs that call whereby all the Prophets and Apoſtles were and are ſent, you will not queſtion our Authority, the Lords work is ſpirituall, 'tis him alone that fits them, and furniſhes them with power from on high to bear witneſs to the Truth: and whereas you ſay before, that you know not our Country nor condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet here you ſay that we are wicked men and deceivers, yea the Miniſters, of Satan, it ſeems you care not what you ſay, but ſay and unſay any thing to root out the innocent, you are lyars, and are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 15. Iſa. 54. 17. Mat. 26. 65.</note> among dogs, murderers, ſorcerers, whoremongers, whoſe portion is in the lake your weapons that you form againſt the truth will not proſper, but the Lord hath diſcovered you to ſome, and is raiſing up a light, whereby your deceits will be laid open, with evill <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 4.</note> thoughts ye judge, who are the Miniſters of Satan, and by the wicked imaginations of your own hearts, counts truth blaſphemie, and puts light for darkneſs, as ever the Prieſts did.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pri. Obj.</hi> 1. By their horrid blaſphemies, which they have uttered, ſecondly by their damnable Hereſies and dangerous errours, which they have avouched.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Blaſphemy and Hereſie whereof we are accuſed we do deny, that which is falſe and errors we deny, for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124878:10"/>
they are without God, and that is your own conditions <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 12.</note> and there ye live without God in the world, and who are <note place="margin">Acts 4. 32.</note> in the truth are of one mind and one heart, now all the Prieſts ſee, which pretend Gods and faith, whether you be in one faith, which if you do conſider, (faith which is the gift of God) ye know it not, it cannot be bought and <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 8. Act. 8. 19. 20. 21.</note> ſold for monie, And ſhew me in the Scripture that ever the Prophets, or Apoſtles had a ſet way of the world, or ſeeked to the world for augmentations or tithes, do <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 8.</note> not ye ſhew here the ſpirit of error, erring from the way of the Apoſtles, And do ye not ſhew your ſelves in the ſame generation of them that <hi>Peter</hi> ſpoke of who live in wickedneſs, and go after the error of <hi>Baalam</hi> and <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 13. 14. 15.</note> in the way of <hi>Cain</hi> to perſecute the righteous ſeed where it is come: here thou makeſt but a rod for thy own back who liveth in uncleanneſs, ſporting in the day <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 3. Jude 10. 2 Pet. 2. 13.</note> time, feaſting, rioting, and ſuch are as naturall bruit beaſts, and what they know they know naturally, whoſe Judgement lingers not, whoſe damnation ſlumbers not, wo unto you, for you go in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and the Lord is coming in power, to pour his plagues upon the beaſt, you beaſts who doe not abide in the truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pri. Obj.</hi> All which tends not onely to the diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the publique peace, and fafety of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but to the ſubverſion of all government.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is falſe, it is not our intention to deſtroy the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for a Commonwealth <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 12.</note> is to bring up all into purity and Juſtice, righteouſneſs we ſet up, own and honour in our ſouls for conſcience ſake; And Juſtice is to keep peace, and that we own, Juſtice is not to make ſtrife, nor debate, but to keep peace, and he bears not the ſword in vain, but he that doth pretend Juſtice, and is partiall, and hath an evil
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:124878:11"/>
eye, and rules with his own will and tyrannic, that we <note place="margin">Jer 25. 10. Hoſea 4. 2. 2 Tim. 3 4. Prov. 21. 22. Prov. 28. 9. Prov. 15. 8. 9. Rom. 8. 22. Pſal. 146. 9. Rom. 13. 12.</note> deny, for the Commonwealth is deſtroyed for want of Juſtice, the Land mourns becauſe of Oathes, the Land mourns becauſe of wickedneſs, drunkennes, fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wrangling carding and diceing, ſhovelbord and bowling, all theſe filthy pleaſures ye luſtfull ones which holds them up we deny, for this cauſe the Creation grones, but Juſtice we own, let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher power for all power is of God, that ſoul is ſubject to the power of God, all theſe works are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, and this Juſtice which keepes peace, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs we own, honour and ſet up in our ſouls.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pri. Obj.</hi> We do in all humility adreſs our ſelves humbly and earneſtly praying as you tender the glory of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The prayers of the wicked are abomination to the Lord, and your humility is fained, it crouches <note place="margin">Prov. 12. 22. Prov. 28. 9. Col. 2. 18. Pſal. 146. 9.</note> to one and perſecutes another, here you ſhew your ſelves to be no Miniſters of Jeſus, Chriſt, for your weapons are carnall ours ſpirituall ſayes the Apoſtle caſting down ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high places, which we wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: and here you ſhew not the ſame ſpirit that was <note place="margin">1 John 4. 6.</note> in the Apoſtles, but of error.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Obj.</hi> And the good of ſo many ſouls as are, and may be indangered by their impious principles and practiſes, that you would be pleaſed to make uſe of that Authoritie wherewith the Lord hath inveſted you ſpeedily to provide for the ſafety of true Religion and the publique peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If you be Miniſters of God, ye are to watch <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 17.</note> for the ſouls, tell me how many ſouls ye have led out of death, but you are in the fleſh, and your Miniſtry is carnall, <hi>Cain</hi> is alive in you, and the ſoul ye know
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:124878:11"/>
not, for it is in the death, therefore diſſemble not thou deceiver, telling people of a ſoul, for thou art him that keepes in the death, and ſhuts the Kingdom of Heaven <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 13. Jam. 5 6. Acts 7. 52.</note> from againſt men and knowes not the ſoul, for that is ſhut up from thy underſtanding, that minde ſhall never know it, thou art a murderer of the juſt, and watcheſt for thy means, and if meu will not give it thee, thou fues them at the law, therefore doſt thou uſe carnall weapons to maintain thee, in thy carnall Miniſtry it ſhewes thy weapons to be carnall and not ſpirituall, ſhewing thy Kingdom to be of this world, And here doth, not thou ſhew forth damnable doctrines; for ſhame bluſh.</p>
                  <p>Impious principles, and practiſes we deny, they are your own, which keepes poor ſouls in death; your preaching the carnall Letter to the carnall minde, and your carnall weapons will not maintain you, but you ſeek to a Magiſtrate, here you ſhame your profeſſion, for where the truth is ſpringing, the pure ſeed ariſing, you cannot ſuppreſs it with your carnall weapon the Letter; then you run to a Magiſtrate without to ſuppreſs it, while we all lived under your Miniſtry, and what you ſpoke we took it for truth as being naturally blind, hearing you blind then you owned us, but God now <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 14.</note> of his infinite love and mercy according to his promiſe hath gathered us, who have been ſcattered in the cloudy and dark day, following ſuch ſhepherds as you which fed your ſelves, and cloathed your ſelves with the wooll, made a prey upon us and ſought for the Fleece, <note place="margin">Ezek. 24 12. 13. 14. 8. 10.</note> but God as he hath ſaid, he hath fulfilled, I will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my ſheep from their mouthes, and my ſheep ſhall be a prey no longer unto them, and will feed them in a good paſture, and we witneſs the Scripture fulfilled,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:124878:12"/>
therefore do you hate us, and ſeek to perſecute them in whom Jeſus Chriſt is made manifeſt, but it is that the <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 29. 2 Tim. 3. 12.</note> Scripture might be fulfilled, he that is born after the fleſh perſecutes him that is born after the ſpirit, and if any man live godly in Chriſt Jeſus he muſt ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; here the Scripture is fulfilled, you ſhew your ſelves to be carnall indeed you muſt have an outward Authoritie to rule your Religion, for ſhame give over your profeſſion, for pure Religion he that lives in it, and walkes in it, hath power over his own tongue, and is kept unſpotted from the world, and doth viſit the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, <note place="margin">Jam. 1. 26. 27.</note> widowes and ſtrangers, and this hath not an outward power to order it, but is guided and ordered by the ſpirit of the Lord, to the Lord himſelf, to whom be praiſes for ever, and ſuch we own in our ſouls, and ſuch ye ſeek to perſecute, and inſtead of relieving and <note place="margin">Rev. 8. 14.</note> receiving ſtrangers, you give them a report or ſcandall, as wanderers, that the Scripture might be fulfilled, who preached the everlaſting Goſpel, the world knew not, and who forſook their own country and ſought for another, whom the world was not worthy of, and you <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 38. Heb. 13. 1. 1 Tim. 5. 10.</note> ſhew your ſelves to be of that generation, he that was a miniſter of God did exhort to receive ſtrangers, by that means ſome received Angels, and the ſame eternal word hath God made manifeſt, and ſent his ſervants to witneſs it forth, and to warn you all of wo and miſery that will come upon all uncleanneſs, and ungodlineſs, and ſome of them you priſon, ſome of them you beat <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 17. Mat. 27. 1. 20. Mat. 26. 3. 4.</note> and mock, and ſcourge in your Synagogues, and ſome of them you hale before Magiſtrates; And the chief Prieſts were ever the ringleaders to ſlay the righteous ſeed where it was born, wherein the Scriptures come to be fulfilled, and you ſhew the fulfilling of them upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124878:12"/>
the children of the Lord, and the words of Jeſus Chriſt true, but he is coming who bears the government upon <note place="margin">Iſa, 9. 6. Pſal. 23. 1. Col. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8. 1 Theſ. 1. 1.</note> his ſhoulders, he alone will rule them, who rules all nations with a rod of iron, he alone will be their teacher, and their Shepherd, he alone rules his Church, who is the head, but this Church is not of this world, nor maintained by any weapon of this world, the true Church is in God, yours vvithout vvho maintain it with a carnall vveapon, you vvould have a ſpeedy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of the truth, vvhere it is riſen, here you ſhevv your ſelves to be of that number vvho call evil good <note place="margin">Iſa. 5. 20. Acts 13. 50. Acts 22. 22.</note> and good evil, and even the generation of them, that vvould ever have had truth ſuppreſſed, when it was ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, <note place="margin">Amos 7. 12.</note> as they ſaid to Chriſt depart out of our coaſts, as they ſaid to <hi>Paul,</hi> 'tis not fit ſuch a fellow ſhould live upon the earth, as to <hi>Amos,</hi> go thy way into <hi>Judah</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie there thatvvas the Kings chappell, and he told them the ſongs of the Temple ſhould be turned into <note place="margin">Amos 8. 3. pla. 119. 120.</note> howling, ſo ſhall that nature, which hath turned <hi>Davids</hi> quakings and trembling into meeter, when ye read them, hats ye keep on, and vvhen ye ſing them hats ye put off, and worſhip the vvorks of your own hands, ſhewing the ſpirit of error.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Obj.</hi> By the checking the vvicked endeavours and proceediugs of theſe men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is the blaſphemer indeed vvhich vvould have the truth chect, and be limitted, It is vvritten the beaſt ſhall blaſpheme God and his Temple, And <note place="margin">Rev. 13. 6.</note> God hath raiſed up a light in many that are Juſtices to reprove that nature in you vvhich is fawning and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, and you will fawn upon them, vvhile they vvill <note place="margin">Mica. 3. 5.</note> give you means, but if they give you no means, then you prepare vvar againſt them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Obj.</hi> Which vve humbly conceive may be at
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124878:13"/>
leaſt by ordering <hi>James Nayler</hi> and <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> being ſtrangers, to depart out of this County, and to return unto their own homes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> You pretended Miniſters of Chriſt, which do but conceive with an earthly power to hinder the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of that which you conceive to be error, which is the eternall truth; and which conceivings ariſe out of pride: Here it ſhews that you have not an infallible judgement, and as it is written, God will ſcatter the <note place="margin">Luke 1. 15.</note> proud in their imaginations: and there is your por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. All people though you now deſpiſe us, and caſt reproches &amp; ſlanders upon us, ye ſhal eternally witneſs us; but it is that the Scripture may be fulfilled, There ſhall be falſe accuſers, incontinent, fierce, deſpiſers of them that are good, having a form of godlineſs, and <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 3, 4, 5, and ſo on.</note> denying the power thereof, vvhich the Apoſtle ſaw then creping into houſes, leading ſilly women captive, always learning, never able to come to the knowledge of the truth, and this doctrine hath ſpread abroad, and ye are in it, having the form are not the people yet lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſilly vvomen, indeed ſome thirty years learning, ſome fourty, ſome fifty, ſome ſixty years learning, yet muſt be taught ſtill, therfore you and your doctrine we utterly deny: For as the Apoſtle ſaith, ye need not that <note place="margin">2 John 2. 20, 27. 1 John 3. 13.</note> any man teach you, you know all things; but theſe vvere not of the vvorld, nor are they of this vvorld, vvho vvitneſs this teaching, nor the Teachers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Object. Francis Howgill</hi> to be of better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, eſpecially towards the Magiſtracie and Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Would you have <hi>Francis Howgill</hi> to be like unto the World your ſelves? Is he going from the power and prince of the air, which rules in you, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:124878:13"/>
children of diſobedience, therefore you hate him. <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 2. Iohn 15. 19.</note> Juſtice he owns, which cuts down corruption, which brings all into an upright carriage and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous way towards God and man: this he owns and honors in his ſoul; the Miniſters of God he owns, and ſuch as bear rule by their means, as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> cried out againſt, ſo do I, and ſuch as are gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy dumb doggs, which ſeek for their gain from <note place="margin">Ier. 5. 30. 31. Iſai. 56. 10, 11</note> their Quarters, which <hi>Iſa.</hi> ſpoke againſt I ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt; and ſuch as are hirelings, which <hi>Micah</hi> cried out againſt, I cry out againſt; and ſuch as ſeek for the fleece, and cloath with the wooll, and feed themſelves with the fat, and kill <note place="margin">Exck. 34. 2, 3.</note> them that are fed, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> cried out againſt ſuch, and fo do I, the pure ſeed being made manifeſt in me, lets me ſee you to be ſuch now, ſee if you can excuſe your ſelves. And all ſuch as who lay heavie burdens upon the people, and ſay they are Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and act thoſe things which Chriſt forbids, I deny: For, ſaith Jeſus Chriſt, they are called of men Maſters, and have the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies, ſtand praying in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, <note place="margin">Matth. 23. 4, 5, 6, 7, 14. Matth. 6. 5.</note> whoſe prayers are heatheniſh, and love the uppermoſt rooms at feaſts and love greetings in the market: and under a pretence make long prayers, devouring Widows houſes. A Widow hath no husband, and Chriſt cryed woe againſt all ſuch, woe was their portion, they painted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with other mens words; painted ſepulchers, full of poyſon within; woe was their portion, and there you are, woe is your portien; he that upholds that which Chriſt cried out againſt, is an Antichriſt, and would you have him uphold An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:124878:14"/>
and deny Chriſt? the world never received <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith, They go in <note place="margin">Iude 11.</note> the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> wo unto them: Are not all the Prieſts here? And would you have this ſet up, which all <note place="margin">1 Iohn 4. 1, 2, 3</note> the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles cried out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt? Where the ſame Spirit is made manifeſt, it ſees you all in error, blaſpheming God and his Temple.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Obj.</hi> And by enjoyning <hi>Tho. Ayrey,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Dixon,</hi> and the reſt of the ſpeakers and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, that live in this County, to abide at their own houſes, ſtudy to be quiet, and do their own buſineſs, labouring in their own calling, which is the Apoſtles Rule, and not to wander up and down the countrey as ſeducers, to draw Diſciples after them, ſave onely as privat men in way of travell about their own occaſions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ. Tho. Ayrey,</hi> and other friends, whom you would have to abide in their own callings, according to the Apoſtles Rule, and ſtudy <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 20. 2 Theſſ. 2. 3.</note> to be quiet, that they own, but the witneſſing forth of the truth doth diſturb the man of ſinne, which makes it now appear; he that is called of the Lord being a ſervant, is the Lords freeman; like wiſe he that is called being free, is Chriſts ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; ye are bought with a price, but be not ye the ſervants of man. Brethren, let every one wherein he is called of the Lord, there abide with the Lord. This call is a holy call, which calls into <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 22, 23, 24.</note> holineſs and righteouſneſs, without which none ſhall ſee the Lord; and this call is not of man. And the Apoſtles Rule we do own and witneſs; but as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:124878:14"/>
for ſeducing people we deny, it is your own pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, we were all ſeduced by you, till God did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 9. Iob 33. 30.</note> us, &amp; bring us out of darkneſs into his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous light, by which we teſtifie againſt all the works of darkneſs; and all who are brought into this light, are one in unity, &amp; as the Apoſtle ſaith, <note place="margin">1 Iohn 1, 7. Iude 20. Iſa. 54. 13.</note> exhort one another daily as the light doth appear, building up one another in the moſt holy faith; and all the children of God ſhall be taught of the Lord, and great ſhall be the peace of them.</p>
                  <p>And the Saints went from houſe to houſe, who were as one ſoul, and met together in ſingleneſs of <note place="margin">Acts 4. 32: Acts 2. 46.</note> heart; here you ſhew your ſelves to be deniers of the practices of the Apoſtles, and of the Saints, and would tread it under foot, and ſhew forth a beaſtly nature, under the pretence of humility, which is meer hypocriſie, and no good at all to poor ſouls, nor for Juſtice, nor for the Common-wealth, nor for pure Religion, nor for the Church of God, nor for godlineſs; but onely for your carnall ſtates, and for fear of loſing your carnall means, doe you rage; for they that own pure Religion, own us, the Church of God owns us, and they that own juſtice own us; and who owns the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, own us; but you who have their forms, and not their power, perſecute us, ſo ſhewing your ſelves to be haters of the truth. The Apoſtles Rule and uſe was, to go up <note place="margin">Matth. 28. 19.</note> and down the countrey, who were Miniſters of God, and rejoyce in them whom he had made Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to witneſs forth the truth, and did plainly declare they had no certain dwelling place. How dare you take the Apoſtles for your cloke, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:124878:15"/>
their words, and act contrary to their life, they were guided by the Spirit of the Lord, and they did draw Diſciples after them, out of the world and earthly mindedneſs, in whom the ſubſtance of all Types and Figures was made manifeſt, they <note place="margin">Acts 4. 32. 2 Tim. 4. 10.</note> had one heart, one minde: ſome indeed did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them, and imbraced the preſent world, as <hi>Demas:</hi> ſo would you have us to forſake the power of truth, and imbrace the preſent world; then we ſhould not abide in the calling, wherein we are called of the Lord. See what a confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in your words.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>And for the Lords gracious guidance of your ſelves in the affairs of ſo great concernment, we ſhall ever pray.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> You are blinde without the truth, and <note place="margin">Prov. 28. 9.</note> your prayers are an abomination unto the Lord, and they who have the gracious guidance of the <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11, 12.</note> Lord will witneſs us; for the free grace of God that brings ſalvation, you have turned into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, it teacheth them to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, them we own; where this grace doth guide, we have unity with them; but where this free grace hath appeared, and is turned into wantonneſs, them we deny, and there is your conditions: the grace of God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in many of the Juſtices, which hath brought them from under your bondage, which will not be your Executioners, to execute your wrath and malice upon the harmleſs, innocent people: It hath been of late, that they who lived under your Miniſtry, the Lord alone was pleaſed to manifeſt himſelf in them, ſo that they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:124878:15"/>
are brought to deny you, and declare what was freely revealed in them; preſently you cryed out againſt them, and had them before Magiſtrates to ſuppreſs the truth, praiſed be the Lord who hath enlightened many by, and with his own light, and is ſetting up his own Kingdom to his own glory; praiſes, praiſesbe unto the Lord God <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 15.</note> Almighty: never did the Apoſtles go to any Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to ſuppreſs people, ſtrangers, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe forth the power of truth in any; where it appears, that you have not the ſame Spirit that was in them: It is the evil in you which would have the truth it ſelf ſuppreſſed. It is of great concernment for you to ſtand up to maintain your Kingdom; for if truth riſe, ye ſhall loſe your Kingdom, eternally ſhall you witneſs us to be no Seducers, be ye witneſſes againſt your ſelves, <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 31.</note> that ye are witneſſes againſt the power of truth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Another Petition put up by the Prieſts in <hi>Weſtmerland.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> TO the Right Honorable, the Juſtices of peace for this County of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which is Right Honorable, is that which is pure, which is of God, which worſhips the Father of heaven and earth; now all people fear <note place="margin">John 5. 41; 44.</note> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and ſee if there be not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption within, that would be honored and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:124878:16"/>
as ye read in all the Scriptures; they who honored the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, cryed againſt deceits; and Ieſus Chriſt teſtified againſt the works of the world; and the Apoſtles teſtified againſt the ſame; but that which was pure, they <note place="margin">John 7. 7.</note> ſet up in their ſouls, and ſo do we, and honor in our ſouls.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> The humble Petition of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Gentlemen, Miniſters of the Goſpel and others, friends and ſervants to Ieſus Chriſt, his Goſpel truths and Ordinances, and the general wealth of this Commonwealth and Nation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Never did the Goſpel Miniſters put up a Petition to a Magiſtrate to maintain the Goſpel, nor the ſervants of Ieſus Chriſt, wherein it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 10. 2 Cor. 10. 14. 2 Cor. 3. 6. 1 John 3. 12. John 4. 21, 22, 23, 24.</note> that you are Miniſters of the Letter, which is carnal and death, and you muſt have a carnal weapon to hold you up; for ſhame give over your Profeſſion: and you profeſs humbleneſs, your humbleneſs is to perſecute; here you ſhew forth the nature of Cain, and void of the knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt; and the Ordinances of Ieſus Chriſt was never ſet up by man, but man who lived in his own will was ever againſt them; and you know not his Ordinances, for they that knew his Ordinances, were not perſecutors; but <hi>Paul</hi> before he was a Miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt, and knew his Ordinances, he came with Letters from the Prieſts, to perſecute the Saints who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in Ieſus Chriſt, and were of one ſoul, and <note place="margin">Acts 9. 2. Acts 22. 4. Acts 20. 7. Acts 4 32.</note> met together, yea in the night time, all night, where it ſhews you have but the form, not the power, which muſt be turned away from, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:124878:16"/>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> Sheweth, that in the late wars, we, or the moſt of us, did expoſe lives, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, eſtates and relations, with all other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal advantages, in the juſt defence of Religion and Liberty, in concurrence with, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the juſt proceedings of our Parliament; after the proſperous effects whereof, we expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſettlement of the grand ends of our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and ſo much the more, as being the promiſe of the Parliament, the vows of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, the price of our prayers, purſes, hazards, loſſes, baniſhments, and the blood of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands our fellow ſervants in the work of God, freely ſacrificed in the quarrel of this Nation: what hath been done in the ſettlement of our Civil Rights, Peace, and wholſom Law, we bleſs God for; and the Parliament as his Inſtruments; nor can we but acknowledge, what hath been done by them in the cauſe of God, as their Acts againſt Adulteries, Fornication, Swearing, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, Sabboth-breaking, Ordinances againſt Promoters of Heretical Doctrines, Acts againſt Ranters or Blaſphemers; may the Lord increaſe the number of theſe things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If ye will own the wholſom Law, ye will own us, but this is but a pretence, for who owns the wholſom Law, denies all corruption; this is but a pretence, whereby ye make a colour to make them that live in the truth, to appear odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto the world, ſetting forth your ſelves unto the world, Phariſee like, and there to make the pure truth odious, through your envious mindes; but the day doth declare all things, your end will <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 13.</note>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:124878:17"/>
make it manifeſt, though you pretend your ſelves to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, yet your ends will <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 13.</note> ſhew you to be bloody <hi>Cains,</hi> and it doth now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to appear, the ſecond birth is brought forth, which doth not own your ſacrifices, this birth you <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 47, 48, 49.</note> ſeek to ſlay.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Obj.</hi> Yet ſo it is, that in this County, ſeverall perſons proſelytes of one <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> and <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> do in the time of our Aſſemblies, ordinarily in a way of contempt and ſcorn, come in anong us, with their hats on; at time of our prayer or ſinging uſed in our Gongregations, ſome of them ſhew violent actions in time of Sermon or prayer, or ſinging, and cry out aloud with horrible clamors, ſlanders, abuſes, reproaches againſt our Miniſters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is falſe, for our friends ſhew no violent actions, but are againſt them, but come peaceably in; and if they be moved by the Lord to cry aloud, who art thou that wilt withſtand the Lord? Do not you read in the Scripture, that the Lord ſent his Prophets, and bad them cry aloud and ſpare not. And as for clamors <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 1.</note> we utterly deny, it is your own: and as for ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, abuſes, reproaches, we utterly deny, it is your own, we are againſt all filthy minds, that give forth reproaches, but we ſpeak the ſame language the Scripture doth from the ſame Word that gave it forth; and your Miniſters which go in that path, which all the holy men of God cried out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, <note place="margin">Iſa. 56. 10. 11.</note> we ſpeak the ſame language againſt them that they did, and by the ſame ſpirit, we ſee them take all people to record to judge, who have a light in their underſtandings, and the fear of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:124878:17"/>
Lord to judge, do not your Prieſts bear rule by your means; and was it not a horrible filthy thing <note place="margin">Ier. 5. 30, 31. Ier. 10. 21.</note> in the time of <hi>Jeremy?</hi> and is not the ſame held up in this age now? and do they not ſeek for their gain from their Quarters, greedy dumb dogs? Do not they take money for that which is not bread? And do they not now ſeek for the fleece &amp;, cloath with the wooll, and make a prey of the people, which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> cryed wo againſt.</p>
                  <p>And are you not Hirelings, which <hi>Micah</hi> cried <note place="margin">Micah 3. 11.</note> againſt, and them that put not into your mouthes, you prepare warrre againſt them, ſue them at the Law, and are you not called of men, Maſters? <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 6, 7, 8.</note> Have not ye the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies? Stand praying in the Synagogues? And do you not lay heavy burdens upon the people, which Jeſus Chriſt cried wo againſt ſuch? Are not you in the ſame ſteps here? Let the Scripture it ſelf judg you; and do not you draw people to thoſe things which there is no Scripture for, telling them of a Sacrament, for which there is no Scripture, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them of ſprinkling infants, which there is no Scripture for, telling people they are Ordinances; all ſuch Ordinances we deny: but the Ordinances of God we own. And doth not the Scripture ſay, He that addes or diminiſhes, the plagues are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 18. Gal. 3. 1.</note> unto him? And were not the Galatians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched who were drawn from the anointing within them, which God had commanded? And do not you draw people to the things there is no Scripture for, telling people they are Ordinances, and are not you in the ſame generation, bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people, drawing them from the Spirit of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:124878:18"/>
Lord within them, to follow your imagination and them that do not, you perſecute them who obey the commands of God, and the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, to walk in the truth in the inward man, which is unknown to you in the world; but <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 22.</note> it is that the Scripture might be fulfilled, They ſhall be hated of all men for my names ſake; and they through fained words, ſhall make merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of you, ſaith the Apoſtle, who go in the way <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 3. 13, 14, 15.</note> of <hi>Cain</hi> to murther, who love the wages of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, who have the Spirit of error, and cauſes people to erre, for the minde that goes from the pure within is erred, and that ſets up <hi>Baal</hi> without, before God; but all whoſe mindes are guided by the Spirit of the Lord up to God, deny all <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, now do not ſay this is railing or falſe accuſing; in theſe ſteps are you, which the holy men of God cryed out againſt, read your ſelves, and let all men judge; and as for coming into your Synagogues with hats on when ye are ſinging of Pſalms, thou Prieſt, haſt not thou one or two caps on, and when ye read Pſalms hats muſt be on, and when ye ſing them hats muſt be off: here ye worſhip the works of your own hands. As <hi>Davids</hi> tremblings, quakings, waſtings, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, roarings till his ſight grew dim, and watered his bed with his tears, and roared all the day long, <note place="margin">Pſal. 6. 23, 6, 7.</note> propheſies, praiſes, prayers, theſe you ſing, having turned them into Rime, crying, Let usſing to the praiſe and glory of God, which is all to his diſhonor: if one ſhould ſee one of you lie in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> condition weeping and roaring, and turn it into Metre, and go among a deal of ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:124878:18"/>
and cry, let us ſing to the praiſe and glory of God, would you not ſay we made a Ryme of you? as you have made of David: All ſuch practiſes and ſingings we deny, but we will ſing with the Spirit, and with Grace and Underſtanding: The Apoſtles which you profeſs in words, you do not read that when they went into the world, they gave <hi>Davids</hi> Experiences in Metre to ſing, but <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 15. Mark 7. 13. Col. 2. 8.</note> was againſt all Traditions of men; and ſo are we now, with the ſame Spirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> To the ſtirring up of woful tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, evident diſturbance of the work, and the turning of the peaceable Aſſemblies of the Church of Chriſt into the groſſeſt confuſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> For ſhame never mention your Churches to be the Churches of Chriſt, which will ſo ſoon be turned into confuſion, do not ſo diſhonor the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo little eſteem his Chruch, which is the Pillar and Ground of Truth; and can the Pillar and Ground of Truth be ſhaken? <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3 15.</note> A Church muſt be that which is the Ground and Pillar of Truth; the Church of Chriſt needs not have a carnal weapon to maintain it, but it is now as it was; they who had received the ſubſtance came into the Aſſemblies, witneſſed forth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and were haled forth, and bruiſed, and <note place="margin">Acts, 7. 48. Acts 21. 30.</note> abuſed, ſtocked and ſtoned, ſo do you us now, almoſt ſmothered in your Aſſemblies; how dare you ſay, ye are peaceable, when ye are ſo in rage againſt a peaceable people, who come among you for your ſouls good, that ye may be directed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, when eternally ye ſhall witneſs us, though now you would devour us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:124878:19"/>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> That their deportent is ſuch, and with ſo continual violence againſt the moſt godly of our Miniſters, in all places in their travels, in the ſtreets, abuſing them with railing language, ſcornful behaviours, walking in the Markets with ſuch great numbers together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for violence, we deny it, it is your own, you ſhew it daily, and in this Petition you make it appear: As for godly Miniſters, ſuch we ſet up, who are made Miniſters by the will of <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 1.</note> God, and not by the will of man; but ſuch as are made Miniſters by <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> ſuch we deny; they who are made Miniſters by the will of Godwill not perſecute any, but here you make your ſelves manifeſt not to be ſuch; for if ye were, ye would own us. As touching railing language, ſcornful behaviour, it is falſe, it is your own, and herein you do abuſe us; ſuch practiſes we deny, which are according to the courſe of the world: Was it not the practiſe of the Apoſtles to diſpute <note place="margin">Epheſſ. 2. 2. Acts 19. 8. Acts 17. 17. Mat. 24. 34, 35</note> dialy in the Markets, in the Schools, in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and their practiſe here you do deny, and ſhew your ſelves to be in that generation that perſecuted the Apoſtles, who now perſecutes us, where the ſame power is made manifeſt, but it is that the Scripture may be fulfilled, for every jot and tittle muſt be fulfilled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition,</hi> And ſcarce paſſing by any not of their judgement, without abuſing words, that it cannot but ſhew us, as no ſmall Symptomes of bad deſigns, ſo no ſmall reaſon to provide for our ſecurity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for abuſive words, it is falſe, it is the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:124878:19"/>
abuſive minde that ſpeaks, which now appears to ſcandal the truth: Several of us, who be of one heart, meet together ſometimes in the Market, and ſometimes in other places; and if we ſee pride and drunkenneſs, and be moved to reprove and exhort; ſee and hear curſed ſpeakers, ſwearers, moved to reprove and exhort them; or men fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and brawling, cozening, cheating, deceitful marehandizing, lying and diſembling, which we ſay wo is upon, do you call this abuſive? and we bid them repent, and turn unto the Lord while they have time, and now to prize it, for the great day of the Lord is coming, wherein every one <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 12.</note> ſhall give an account: And the Apoſtle warned all, ſmall and great, to turn unto the Lord and repent, which we cannot but do the ſame, who have found mercy of the Lord, who brought us to repentance, and changed our lives; and this is it which you call abuſive: And poor creatures, ye need not ſeek for ſecurity, for there is none of them who are friends of the truth, and in the truth that will hurt you: Now do you ſhew your ſelves to walk in the Apoſtles practiſe, or quite againſt it: here you openly ſhew your ſelves to be men who would uphold iniquity and vice, and would not have it reproved, but perſecute ſuch who reprove the wicked; whoſe righteous ſouls are vexed, as <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 8. Prov. 10. 24. Jer. 17 5.</note> juſt <hi>Lots</hi> was, with your filthy Converſation, who uphold iniquity, and live in it: Tis written, <hi>The wicked ſhall fear, where there is not fear;</hi> and did not the true Prophet ſay? <hi>Curſed is he that makes fleſh his arm and outs his ſtrength in man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition,</hi> That it is their great deſign to ſtir
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:124878:20"/>
up the ſpirits of people againſt the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> in general, without diſtinction, ſetting forth and ſending abroad daily, almoſt Libels and ſlanders againſt the Office as needleſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Spirit of God, if it be raiſed up, <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 10.</note> we do witneſs it will teſtifie againſt you, and all your practiſes; and whereas we are moved to write abroad, ſhewing forth the errors and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of you, which as a ſcandal you call to be Libels: but if ever you own the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles, ye will own them, which are given forth by the ſame power and Spirit: and all your Offices which are made by man, and are of man, we deny, and ſlanders we deny, they are your own, and now you vent them forth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> Terming them as or under the names of Antichriſts, Antichriſts Merchants, Tythe Mongers, Robbers, Deceivers, Miniſters of the world, Prieſts, Murtherers, Conjurers, Devils, and attempting to make Proclamations in the open markets to the ſaid effect.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Are you not Antichriſts? do not you act thoſe things Chriſt forbids, and upholds that which Chriſt doth forbid, ſhewing your ſelves to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts? do not you mount up into the higheſt places in Aſſemblies, are called of men-Maſters? <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 2 Pet. 2. 3.</note> which Chriſt forbids, and ſaid to his, be ye not called ſo: And do not you buy and ſell the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, make merchandize of it; when as the Miniſter of God ſaid, that the gift of God could not be <note place="margin">Acts 8. 18. 23. 19, 20.</note> bought and ſold for money; and ſaid he was in the gall of bitterneſs who thought to buy it: and here you ſhew your ſelves to be in the gall of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:124878:20"/>
repent, repent, that the thoughts of your hearts may be changed: and <hi>Job</hi> ſaid, that <note place="margin">Job 28. 15, 16.</note> the wiſdom of God cannot be bought and ſold for money, nor gold, nor pearls, nothing is to be compared unto it; and do not you ſhew your ſelves to be merchants of the Letter, for the gift of God cannot be bought and ſold: And do not you openly ſhew your ſelves to take Tythe of people, and do not walk according to the Law: <hi>Levi,</hi> who received Tythes, the ſtrangers, father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <note place="margin">Deu. 26. 12, 13 Deut. 14. 29.</note> and widows were to come within his gate and be filled, which ye do not ſo, ſhewing the ſpirit of error, and yet would be maintained in your deceit, but God in his infinite love hath raiſed up <note place="margin">Luke 1. 79.</note> a light, gathering his people from you, diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your deceit.</p>
                  <p>Are ye not Robbers? do not you ſteal the words of the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and ſell them for money; and ſo are Theives and Robbers which Ieſus Chriſt ſpoke of, which goes not in at <note place="margin">Jer. 23. 30. Iohn 10. 1.</note> the door, but climb another way; and that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration perſecuted Chriſt, and here you ſhew your ſelves to be perſecuting them in whom he is riſen.</p>
                  <p>Are ye not deceivers? when as you draw peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to thoſe things God never commanded, and tell people they are Ordinances of God; As ſprinkling of infants, and ſaying the Steeple-houſe <note place="margin">Col. 2. 22. 20. 21.</note> is the Chruch, and the houſe of God, and tells people ye are the Miniſters of God, when he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſent you, but ſtudies a Devination of your own brain, and not from the mouth of the Lord: here you ſhew your ſelves to be Conjurers, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:124878:21"/>
hold up outward Temples, Traditions and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Tythes, Formal Singing, Praying; do you not here ſhew your ſelves to be Miniſters of the world; for what is acted outwardly is worldly, your original is worldly, your Hebrew, Latine and Greek is worldly, your Church is worldly; but the Saints Church is in God, as <hi>Paul, Silvanus</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1. 1. 1 John 3. 15.</note> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> to the Church of the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> which was in God: Do not you ſhew your ſelves to be murtherers, in the generation of the Prieſts <hi>Cain</hi> like? do you not ſhew it openly, do not ye ſeek to perſecute and put in priſon: ſome you have impriſoned, ſome you have haled out of your Aſſemblies, ſome ye have ſtoned and buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: do not you ſhew your ſelves to be of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration with the Prieſts, whoſe Miniſtry was worldly, and ſo ever the Miniſtry of the Letter perſecuted the Miniſters of the Spirit: ſo it is now; here the Scripture is fulfilled.</p>
                  <p>And are not you of the Devil? they that abide not in the truth, are of the Devil: and do not <note place="margin">2 John 1. 9.</note> you ſhew your ſelves to be Devils, of the Devil, Murtherers; he was a murtherer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and which of you can ſay, you come to the beginning, but are ſeeking now to deſtroy the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, a peaceable, harmleſs people, to bring them into priſon, and into bondage; do not you ſhew your ſelves to be murtherers, ſeeking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; as the Iews, who ſaid God was their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when they went about to kill Chriſt, and were of their father the Devil, doing the luſts of their father; which generation you ſhew your <note place="margin">John 8. 44.</note> ſelves to be in, envying the righteous ſeed, where it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:124878:21"/>
is brought forth, but God of his infinite power and love, doth preſerve his little ones from your hands, from devouring them, to him be all honor, and glory, and praiſe, who maintains his own truth, and ſets up his own Kingdom, whoſe ſword is his Word, and to it ſhall all Nations bow; though you and many others, who are now fighters againſt <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 12.</note> God, and would have the Magiſtrates to help you, tis hard for you to kick againſt the pricks; but <note place="margin">Acts 9. 5.</note> God hath raiſed up a light in many of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to ſee your deceits, and your envy is made appear.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> That their main drift is, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the people againſt the Miniſtry by reaſon of Tythes, crying out with open clamor againſt Tythes, as Unlawful, Antichriſtian, to the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary overthrowing of the Laws, to that purpoſe bringing an odium upon the Government, and tending to ſtir up ſedition in the people, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their due obedience from the Laws and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The receiving of Tythes is Antichriſtian: Are ye all blinde? did ever any of the Apoſtles or Chriſt receive Tythes, or commanded any ſuch thing? was not he the end of the Law? and where the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt is, it teſtifies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, who neither walk according to the Law nor Goſpel: for whom he made Miniſters, <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 10. 8.</note> he ſent them forth freely, without a bag, or ſtick, or ſcrip, without two coats, freely ye have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, freely give, the workman is worthy of his meat; but here's no Tythes, no Augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: now you are not here in the ſteps of them
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:124878:22"/>
whom Chriſt ſent forth, but ſhews that you run before you be ſent; and where the Spirit of the Lord is ſtired up in any, it cries againſt all ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous wayes.</p>
                  <p>Whereas you ſpeak of a neceſſary overturning the Law, there in you ſhew forth your weakneſs, and a mingle-mangle of your mind. As for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>Odium</hi> upon the government, it is falſe; for the righteous Law of God we honor, and ſet up in our ſouls, and that is to govern that which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly and unjuſt. As for ſtirring up ſedition, as for drawing people from the righteous Law of God, that is your own condition under a pretence of making people believe we deny government and the law; that is falſe.</p>
                  <p>If you vvere as carefull and vvatchfull in your own Kingdom, over drunkards, blaſphemers, ſwearers, fighters, liars, if you were as watchfull over them, then you might ſay you vvere friends of the government, and of the righteous law; but if any come into the markets, and reprove ſuch things, or read a paper in the market againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, ſuch you hale out, ſtone and perſecute; herein you ſhew there is no friendſhip with the Law; but if a man bring a ſieve of Ballads, or Jeſt books, Rimes or Theames, and ſing theſe in the markets; thoſe are ſuffered, theſe Libels are not minded; which ſhews now your venome againſt the truth, and againſt them that ſpeak from the mouth of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Petition.</hi> That beſides what others perhaps may know of the blaſphemies of them, we do plainly ſee and know, that their practiſes do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:124878:22"/>
ſavour of Sorcery, the quakings, ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, roarings, foamings, and ſuch as we never <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 1. Jam. 2. 4.</note> heard of, but ſuch as were poſſeſſed of the Divel, of perſons at their meetings, and eſpecially of young children.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> You can judge no otherwiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the generation of them that perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted Chriſt, calling truth blaſpnemy; but blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy we do deny, ſorcery practices we deny, and we ſee you in that geeration, in witchcraft and ſorcery, drawing people to follow your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, who have painted your ſelves with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers words, myſtery, witchcraft, all who are drawn from the Spirit of the Lord within, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your imaginations, are bewitched by you with evill thoughts.</p>
                  <p>An as for quakings, roarings, tremblings, you ſay you never heard of, and before you profeſſed your ſelves to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, and yet are ignorant of the Scriptures, you are blind, and do you make your ſelves ſo openly blind and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, as not to hear of quaking? <hi>Moſes</hi> when he heard the Lord ſpeak unto him, he trembled, and durſt not behold; and <hi>Moſes</hi> quaked and excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly feared, and the whole mount quaked. And <note place="margin">Acts 7. 32.</note> 
                     <hi>Daniel</hi> when he heard, trembled, and his breath and ſtrength was gone. And <hi>Habakkuk</hi> he trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, <note place="margin">Dan. 10. 11. Habak. 5. 16. Acts 9. 6. 1 Cor. 2. 3. Poil. 2. 12. Job. 4. 14.</note> &amp; quivered, his belly ſhook, that he might reſt in the day of trouble. And <hi>Paul</hi> he trembled when he came among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> he was with them in much weakneſs and trembling, and he bade the Saints work out their own ſalvation with fear and trembling. And <hi>Job</hi> he trembled,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:124878:23"/>
and <hi>David</hi> he quaked and trembled, his bones did <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 120. Iſai. 66. 2. 5.</note> quake. And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaid, Hear the word of the Lord, all ye that tremble at his word. And Chriſt ſaid, Your brethren that hated you, and caſt you out for my names ſake, ſaid, Let the Lord be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified; but he ſhall appear to your joy, but they ſhall be aſhamed. And do not you caſt us out in your mouthes, as the filth and off-ſcouring of the world? Is not here the Scripture fulfilled? <note place="margin">Jer. 5. 22.</note> And <hi>Jeremy</hi> which was ſent to ſpeake unto the people the word of the Lord, ſaid, Hear this, a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh people without underſtanding, will ye not fear me? will ye not tremble at my preſence, who have placed the ſand for the bound of the ſea, and ſuch a people then upheld Prieſts that bare rule by their means, ſo doe you now. And <hi>David</hi> he roared, and watered his bed with his tears, and his fleſh waſted till he could number his <note place="margin">Pſal. 6.</note> bones; will you ſay that all theſe were poſſeſſed with the Divell? The ſame power of God we witneſs now, as was then, and we witneſs the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture fulfilled, and have a cloud of witneſſes, which are recorded in the Scriptures, it ſhews that they have not heard his voyce which ſhakes the <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 1. Pſal. 2. 19, 20.</note> earth; who denies the Letter, are not Miniſters of the Letter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Pet.</hi> And Giving too ſad a ſuſpition of it, and the more by reaſon of the known ſuſpitions upon <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> to deal with the Divell before ever he came to us in theſe parts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whereas you ſpeak of a known ſuſpition, you have a ſuſpition and know nothing; he that knows doth not ſuſpect, but hath an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:124878:23"/>
judgment to judge truth from error (with evil thoughts ye judge, as they did of Jeſus Chriſt, <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 4. Mat. 10. 15.</note> who called the Maſter of the Houſe <hi>Beelzebub;</hi> which generation it appears you are of. And as for dealing with the Divel, it is your own; for I do witneſs the works of the Divell deſtroyed: for where Ieſus Chriſt is made manifeſt, the works of the Divell are deſtroyed; therefore do you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute me, becauſe I teſtifie againſt you, that your deeds are evill. And dealing with the Divel I ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny, and the works of darkneſs; for he that is born of God ſins not, neither can he, becauſe <note place="margin">1 John 3. 8. 9.</note> the ſeed of God remains in him, and the evill one cannot touch him: but if they call the maſter of the houſe <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> what will they do unto the children? So it was, Jeſus Chriſt, Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, had that portion of the world, it is the ſame now where he is made manifeſt in any, the ſame generation, perſecutes, it is no ſtrange thing. <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 25.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Petition.</hi> That we know the Principles of ſome of their followers, are againſt ſubjection to Magiſtrates, againſt diſtinction amongſt men, and the practices of the moſt is ſuch, that there is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of relations, children profeſſedly refuſing ſubjection to their Parents, and ſervants to their maſters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whereas you ſay we are not ſubject to juſtice, that is falſe; for conſcience ſake let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher power: for all power is of God, and he that reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God: So for conſcience ſake, we honor juſtice, and all men in the Lord; but as for reſpecting perſons, we deny, for the Scripture <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1, 2.</note>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:124878:24"/>
denies the ſame, he that reſpects perſons commits ſin, and is a tranſgreſſor of the Law; He that was a miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt, ſaid this, Here you <note place="margin">James 2. 9. Rev. 22. 15.</note> ſhew your ſelves to be without, and no miniſters of God, but would have others to tranſgreſs the law of God. O falſe accuſers! where do any walk ſtubbornly againſt their parents but for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake they cannot yeeld to thoſe things which carnally they would have them act, as follow the worſhip of the world without them, and not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip God in Spirit, and ſet up your teachers of the world. God hath raiſed up a light in many <note place="margin">John 4. 23. Luke 1. 79. Mat. 21. 16. Mat. 11. 25.</note> young children, draws them to himſelfe, and you ſpue forth your venom againſt them ſervants and children, becauſe they will not hold you up, and now when you are like to fall. If Chriſts words ſhould be fulfilled where he ſaith, Call no man fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon earth; and he that loves Father or <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 9. Mat. 10. 37.</note> mother more then me, is not worthy of me, what would you ſay to that? Fathers and mothers paſs away, and that love that is in the fleſh; but the Father, the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, is for ever, and who owns him, will not walk in diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to any thing, but the evill; and if God put into the mouth of any ſervants to ſpeak, that doth <note place="margin">Acts 2. 18.</note> not take them from faithfulneſs in the outward to their maſters where they are: But you accuſers, which have the form of godlineſs, but deny the power, ever ſhew forth your ſelves; Where do any of the ſervants maſters go to complain to the Magiſtrates? But you Prieſts ſhew your ſelves <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5, 13.</note> buſie about other mens matters, only to hold up your own profits, and accuſe the juſt with many falſe and ſcandalous ſlanders.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:124878:24"/>
                     <hi>Pr. Petition.</hi> That we are ſenſible what confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, diviſions, tumults and parties are made by theſe mens diſturbances, and cannot but with ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſpirit, remember that ſuch ſmall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings have in other nations grown to eat out their peace, and ſtagger the foundation of their States, as alſo to lay it before you, what advantage it gives for the common enemy, weakens the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments intereſt in the peoples hearts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truth ever ſtirred up confuſion where it was though it lay cloſe till truth came, <note place="margin">Luke 12. 49.</note> as you read in the Scriptures, Chriſt came to put fire in the earth; and the Apoſtles where they came in the markets or Synagogues, who witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed forth the ſubſtance, to draw people to it, to ſerve the Lord in newneſs of life, to come up into the everlaſting truth and peace, then every one ſtood up in his own imagination and thoughts, as you do now to oppoſe the truth, and ſaid they would turn the world up ſide down.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Petition.</hi> To ſee ſuch perſons unreſtrained, creats diſcontents, and laies a clear foundation for civill wars, or at leaſt advantage to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> or <hi>French</hi> now in arms againſt us, to carry on their wicked intentions with greater facility.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The intention of your mind is to have truth reſtrained, which takes away the occaſions of all wars, and brings into love and true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſs, and there is nothing diſcontent with us, but that which doth not abide in the truth. And wheras thou ſpeakeſt of weakning the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments intereſt, and laying a foundation of new war: This is hatched in your own minds, ſo to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:124878:25"/>
incenſe ignorant people, it is your own intereſt that you fear; for if the Parliament ſhould take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your Tythes and your means, little love would appear to them; for it hath been already ſaid by you, that the Parliament hath opened a gap for all blaſphemings, but the hands of evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers we do not ſtrengthen; and you are the men that raiſe up civill warres againſt them that live peaceably and love peace, and go about to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ocaſions of all warres. For the world raiſes up a perſecution and a civill warre againſt a peaceable people, whoſe intents are to bring up all to God, to live in unity one with another, to be of one heart and one mind, and one ſoul to ſeive God in newneſs of life, whom Chriſt Ieſus hath ſet free from the Traditions and Rudiments of the world. Now who are ſet free from the world, you bring under your bondage, and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them, if they will not obey you, ſhewing forth the nature of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> not letting Iſrael go to ſerve God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> Therefore as you are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Magiſtrates, vve are freemen born of <hi>England,</hi> and deſiring ſomthing more as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments under God with others of your preſent peace, do beg an chalenge from you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now you ſhew your complements: we are no breakers of peace, who owns the peace, owns us; and he that bears this ſword that cuts <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> down all corruption and filthineſs, owns us. For there is no peace to the vvicked ſaith God, and this you ſhall all find vvho vvould have peace to that vvhich muſt die, it is your eternall peace, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:124878:25"/>
eternal ſouls good, that we are moved of the Lord to ſpeak unto you for, which eternally you ſhall witneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> 1. Your timely looking unto the Peace of England, that it ſeems too evidently to be endeavored to be rent aſunder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Juſtices that keeps peace, we honor and ſet up, and wait all for the peace; but your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in this, is to have truth ſuppreſſed, and wickedneſs flouriſh, and the works of darkneſs not diſcovered: here is Juſtice weakned, and the hand of evil doers ſtrengthened againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, which ever the chief Prieſts did; for they asked to releaſe <hi>Barabas,</hi> and crucifie Jeſus the innocent, and gathered the Elders againſt him, to ſeek to put him to death; ſo do you now, where he is made manifeſt, who are of the ſame gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> 2. The protection of our ſelves, and our Miniſters from violence, or diſturbance in our worſhip of God, and ſuppreſſion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Where did the Saints or Miniſters of God ſeek to a Magiſtrate to protect their worſhip? but <note place="margin">Acts 24. 5.</note> on the contrary, they were perſecuted of ſuch, which the Jews and Prieſts did incenſe them to, which is the ſame you do now; as the Jews who came againſt Paul, and ſaid he was a peſtilent fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, a mover of ſedition, a ſtirrer up of hereſie, a Ring-leader of the Sect of the Nazarens, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the world up ſide down, and teaches contrary to our Cuſtom, and this holy place; he told them, God dwelled not in Temples made with hands,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:124878:26"/>
neither was he worſhipped with mens hands, <note place="margin">Acts 17. 24, 25</note> which outward cuſtom you are upholding now, in the ſame nature that they were in; when the Jews brought <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Felix,</hi> holding up their own cuſtoms by an outward Law, as impriſoning him, <hi>Paul</hi> had no Law to maintain him, but the Law of God, and the eternal Word to guide him; and <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 4. Gal. 1. 1. Iſaiah 33. 22.</note> the ſame we do witneſs, againſt all the powers of men, but the power of God let every ſoul be ſubject too.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> 3. Execution of the Statute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sabboth breakers, and ſuch as under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religion, are in no Religious Aſſemblies that day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> All that live in pretence of Religion, and not in power, is nothing; all that owns pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, owns us; and all that owns the Sabboth, the eternal Reſt, the eternal day, owns us; but while people have met together to ſet up you, who in the week day invented faſhions, and on that day put it on, ſo the eye goes out looking at new faſhions, and in the week day follows oathes, drunkenneſs, prophaneneſs, pleaſures, and ſuch practiſes we deny; but to live righteouſly, ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this preſent world, this we own; and whom you finde wrangling, walking in uncleanneſs, curſed ſpeaking, fighting, drunkenneſs, upon ſuch you ſhould lay the Law: for the Law was made for the Lawleſs, but you pretended Miniſters, ſeek to bring upon us bounds, who are redeemed from theſe ways, through the love and power of God; if you were the Miniſters of God, you would go about to bring people from under all Law, up to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:124878:26"/>
God, but you ſhew your ſelves to be of that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration which ſhut the Kingdom of heaven from <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 13.</note> men, which Kingdom is a Kingdom of peace, this we witneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> 4. Charge to all differing judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to meet together each Lords day peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, and not to ſpread themſelves to ſeveral places for diſturbance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If any be moved by the Lord to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Aſſemblies, to ſpeak the word of the Lord unto them, for your ſouls eternal happineſs, would you have this limitted? this is your intent, to limit the Holy one of Iſrael: As for diſturbance, we all deny, and to draw people up to God, that we do, out of all carnal ways; for God is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and will be worſhipped in ſpirit, and in truth, and this worſhip we own; and who are here, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies all your Temples and Prieſts; herein is one Prieſt, Jeſus Chriſt, the Biſhip of our ſouls; for they who received the Subſtance, denyed the Prieſts, and they met together the firſt day of the week, and when any was moved to go forth, they went and witneſſed forth the Subſtance to them that lived in the Shadows: this we do, and now to deny you Prieſts (being ye cannot witneſs your call) the Temple which God never commanded, they that are in the Temples of God do: This dark Miniſtry hath long reigned over people, and kept them in bondage, underimitated forms, but <note place="margin">Luke 1. 79.</note> now God is raiſing a light in his people, to gather them up to himſelf, to live in love and unity one with another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Pet.</hi> 5. Suppreſſion of perſons living without any calling.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:124878:27"/>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then this ſuppreſſion muſt come upon your ſelves; for you cannot witneſs that ever you were called of God, or ſent forth by Jeſus Chriſt to preach the everlaſting truth; for if you were you would not raiſe up perſecution againſt them that witneſs a call from the Lord: who of you receive whipping, ſtocking, ſtoning, priſoning, buffeting, and haling us out of your Aſſemblies, who do pretend your ſelves to be Miniſters of Chriſt: wait to have that ſuppreſſed in your ſelves that perſecutes, then you will not ſeek to oppreſs the juſt for your own ends, that ye might be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in your beaſtly worſhip, and your Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ways.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> 6. And your witneſſing againſt all blaſphemers of the name of God, eſpecially ſuch as are contained in the Acts of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If you would have them witneſs againſt all Blaſpemers, then they muſt witneſs againſt you, who calls evil good, and good evil, and vents forth ſo many Blaſphemies againſt them who live in the power of truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Petition.</hi> And if the application of any effectual remedy, lie not within your power, that you will dleaſe to joyn with us in this deſire, and tranſmit this cauſe to the knowledge of the Right Honorable the Councel of State, as a cauſe ſo nearly concerning the peace of <hi>England,</hi> and we ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> You would have a Law or an Act forth, under a pretence to ſuppreſs the truth, under the name of Blaſpemy, becauſe it doth ſhake your Kingdom, who live in your ſelf ends: for ranting
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:124878:27"/>
ways and blaſpemy, we utterly deny, and takers of Gods name in vain, which you do in every word you ſpeak, becauſe ye know him not: he is merciful to the juſt and unjuſt, but you ſhew your cruelty againſt the juſt, and perſecute them.</p>
                  <p>Here you ſhew forth your ſerpentine nature, and would beget others in the ſame envy to joyn with you, to be the ſtronger to tread down the truth; as it is written, The Beaſt ſhall make war againſt the Lamb but the Lamb get the victory, praiſes, praiſes for ever, be to the Lord God Almighty; you ſay the Lords Prayer, <hi>Forgive us, as we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us;</hi> but you perſecute them that ſeeks your ſouls health, ſeeking you, and not yours, their prayers are an abomination to the Lord. And what is Right and Honorable, will <note place="margin">Prov. 28. 9. Iohn 5. 44. Prov. 20. 3. Rev. 14. 7.</note> deny all you, and your Petitions; for they who owns God and Chriſt owns us; who owns peace owns us, and we them in our ſouls; but all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders of God and godlineſs, who live in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs and ungodlineſs, denying the power that cuts down iniquity, which we own and ſet up: Therefore all people whoſe mindes are now bent to raiſe up perſecution, and Prieſts who ſtands railing in your Pulpits, incenſing ignorant people againſt harmleſs innocent people: Are not you laying here a foundation for a new war? and ſo digging a pit for your ſelves to fall into; you need never fear them who live in the power of truth, to raiſe up an outward war, but it is your falſe ſuggeſtion, to incenſe people to make them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve lies; but God hath raiſed up alight in peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and in Magiſtrates, which diſcerns all your intents.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="order_and_response">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:124878:28"/>
               <div type="order">
                  <head>An Order that was ordered at the Seſſions at <hi>Appleby</hi> in <hi>Weſtmerlrnd.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ORdered, That whoſoever ſhall hereafter diſturb any Miniſter in the Publike Exerciſe of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, within this County, or give any ſcandalous, oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious terms against any of them, ſhall be apprehended by the Conſtables or Church wirdens of the place, where the offence ſhall be committed, and brought before the next Juſtice of the peace, to finde Sureties for his or her good behaviour, and upon refuſing to finde ſuch Sureties, to be committed to the common Goal, till willingly they ſhall do the ſame or be from thence delivered by due courſe of Law: And likewiſe, all ſuch perſons as me t in great numbers and Aſſemblies in the night time, within this County, ſhall be apprehended, and bound to good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour as aforeſaid.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts. Order.</hi> ORdered, That whoſoever ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after diſturb any Miniſter in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Exerciſe of his Miniſtry within this County.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Law of the Land doth give free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to ſpeak, after the man hath done: and here you ſeem to make a new Parliament, and new Laws, contrary to the Law of the Land; and here you ſhew your ſelves not to do Juſtice, not act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the Law of the Land, and the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 30, 31. Num. 11. 28, 29 Num. 12. 7. Heb. 3 2. 1</note> Law of God: <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, who witneſſed forth the Law, and was Ruler in the Law, he wiſhed that all Gods people were Prophets: now he was faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the Law of God, which God had command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:124878:28"/>
him: and here thou ſhewſt to act contrary to the Law of the Land, and turn'ſt thy ſelf out of thy juſtice: And the Miniſter of God ſaid, that all might ſpeak in the true Church, and if any thing were revealed to him that fate by, let the firſt hold his peace; for you may all propheſie one by one, that all may be edified, and God may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified; for the ſpirits of the Prophets are ſubject <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 30 31. 32.</note> to the Prophets: and here you do ſhew your ſelves to be no Prophets, nor no Miniſters, and your Church no Church; if any ſhould come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Aſſemblies, and ſit by, and ſomething be revealed to him, and he ſay, Let the other hold his peace; and you ſay, he diſturbs the Miniſter: <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 19. Mat. 10. 17. 23 Heb. 11. 36, 37. Acts 7, 58. 59.</note> here you would quench the Spirit, and limit the holy one: And here is the Scripture fulfilled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; If they ſhould ſpeak you would ſcourge them in your Synagogues, nay, ſtone them, beat them, and impriſon them, and mock them: and is not Jeſus Chriſts words fulfilled here? And they ſhall perſecute you: and now you ſhew it forth; bluſh for ſhame, and never take him for a cloak, <note place="margin">Gen. 48. Mat. 23. 33, 34, 35. Acts 21. 30. 2 Pet. 2. 12.</note> for you are in the ſame Generation of them that perſecuted them who lived in the truth; be ye witneſſes unto your ſelves, that you are in the ſame nature that they were in, that hailed <hi>Paul</hi> out of the Temple; how dareſt thou then take his words into thy mouth: O brazen face beaſt, that doth not abide the truth!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prieſts Order,</hi> Or give any ſcandalous, opprobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous terms againſt any of them, ſhall be apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Conſtables or Church Wardens of the place, where the offence ſhall be committed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:124878:29"/>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which you call ſcandalous terms, is the truth upon the deceit, according to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 1.</note> For <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, they were bewitched, them that were drawn from the Spirit of the Lord within them, to carnal circumciſion without them: ſo do you bewitch the people now, as ſprinkling of infants, and telling them of a Sacrament, which there is no Scripture for, and drawing them from <note place="margin">Jer. 5. 30, 31.</note> their Teacher within them; for <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaid, they bear rule by their means, and held up the horrible filthy thing that was committed in the Land; and <note place="margin">Iſa. 56. 10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaid, they were greedy dumb dogs, which could not bark, which never had enough, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their gain from their quarters: And all people conſider, do not all the Prieſts of the world bear rule by their means, and ſeek for their gain from their quarter: we ſpeak the truth, we have a cloud of witneſſes: and <hi>Micah</hi> ſaid, the Prieſts <note place="margin">Micah 3. 5.</note> preached for hire, and he that did not put into their mouthes, they prepared war againſt him: Do not you Prieſts ſue men at the Law, if they do not put into your mouthes? nay, of your own Church: And yet profeſſes your ſelves to be Teachers of Chriſt: O for ſhame bluſh! Paul <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 1, 5.</note> that was a Miniſter of Chriſt, ſaid to the Saints that went to Law, there was not a wiſe man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: and here thou ſhewſt thy ſelf to be no Miniſter of Chriſt, no not to walk according to the Letter, no not a wiſe man. Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſees, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, them that were called of men Maſters, and ſo are you, them that had the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies, and ſo have you; ſtand praying
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:124878:29"/>
in the Synagogues, and ſo do you; and vvith a <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 6, 7, 8, 10, 23.</note> pretence make long prayers, devouring Widows houſes, and Ieſus Chriſt cried vvo againſt ſuch, and you hold up thoſe things which Chriſt doth forbid, and you do make men believe you are Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, and that Chriſt hath ſent you, and act thoſe things vvhich Chriſt doth forbid, and the ſame wo is upon you that was upon them, that held up thoſe practiſes; and the Apoſtle ſaid they had forſaken the right vvay, vvo unto them, for they have gone in the vvay of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam.</hi> Are not <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 15. 3. Iude 11.</note> you in envy like <hi>Cain,</hi> do not you ſhew it forth, and run after the vvages of <hi>Balaam,</hi> for gifts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and covetouſneſs, vvho make merchandiſe upon the people, and as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaid, they ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Fleece, and eat the Fat, and cloath vvith the Wooll, and kill them that were fed, and made a prey upon them, and devoured them. But as the <note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 23: 10. 14.</note> Lord ſaid, I vvill gather them from their mouths, and feed them upon the mountains. And this Scri ture we witneſſe to be fulfilled, praiſe and honor be to the Lord. And you Prieſts do not you ſeek after the wooll? Will you make a lye of Scripture? Friends, do not ſay this is railing, for I ſpeak the truth, and have a cloud of witneſſes, the prophets and Apoſtles which ſpoke from the ſame Word which is made manifeſt, and lets us ſee the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits as they ſaw them, and cry againſt them; and <note place="margin">Iſai. 62. 1.</note> for Sions ſake we cannot hold our peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Order.</hi> And brought before the next Iuſtice of the peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Prophets and the Apoſtles that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:124878:30"/>
witneſſed forth theſe things, were haled to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and before the Magiſtrates, as you read in <note place="margin">Acts 21. 34. Acts 12. 4, 5. Acts 16. 22, 23, 24.</note> the Scripture; ſo here is the Scripture fulfilled, by the ſame generation, <hi>Paul</hi> was haled out of the Temple, and was had to priſon, who witneſſed forth the ſubſtance of all Types, ſigures, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows. And though you have gotten <hi>Pauls</hi> words, you ſhew your ſelves to be of the ſame generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">Act. 21. 30, 31</note> haling them out of the Temple. Be witneſſes againſt your ſelves, that you are perſecuters of the power of truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pr. Petition.</hi> To find ſureties for his or her good behaviour; and upon refuſe to find ſuch ſureties, to be committed to the common Goal, till willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſhall do the ſame, or be from thence deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by due courſe of Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Who are redeemed by the pretious blood of Jeſus Chriſt, from their vain converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 31. 1 Pet. 1. 18, 19 Phil. 3. 20, Rom. 8. 14.</note> who live up to God, who are the Miniſters of God, guided by the Spirit of God, need not not have a law laid upon them, which is made for the lawleſs, to bind them to good behaviour. The end of our miniſtry is to bring all men from <note place="margin">Rom. 7 6. Gal. 3. 19. Iam. 4. 1.</note> under the occaſions of all laws into good behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to ſerve God in newneſs of life. For the law is made to bind them to good behaviour, who walk in drunkenneſs, ſwearing, and fighting, and this is at liberty, where there is misbehaviour, and you lay your law upon us, which you cannot accuſe; ſo <hi>Barabbas</hi> is ſet at liberty, and <note place="margin">Matth 27. 26. Acts 13. 10,</note> Chriſt is perſecuted and priſoned; and here you would lay your law upon them whom you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not accuſe: therfore wo unto you liars, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the counſell of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:124878:30"/>
                     <hi>Pr. Petition.</hi> And likewiſe all ſuch perſons as meet in great numbers and aſſemblies in the night time within this County, ſhall be apprehended and bound to good behaviour, as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This law it ſeems is made new, while we met together, to card, to dance in Alehouſes, to vain pleaſures, we were not accuſed; but now all theſe practiſes are denied, who are gathered by the ſpirit of the Lord, to exhort one another day <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 13. Acts 20. 7, 8, 9 Iude 20. 1 Pet. 4, 10.</note> and night, both which is according to the Saints practice, and Rule; <hi>Paul</hi> preached untill midnight, and they met together and did exhort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and preached one to another, and builded up one another in the moſt holy faith; and herein we witneſs the Scripture fulfilled amongſt us, praiſed be the Lord: by this you would not have us to walk according to the Scripture, wherein you bring us to misbehaviour, and we ſee and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs you are the ſame generation as they were in that perſecuted <hi>Paul</hi> and the Saints then which met together in the night time. If <hi>Paul</hi> and the Saints were here now, you which have got the form of words, you would do it unto them, as you do unto us; for all is one.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Some Pleadings that paſſed between Juſtice <hi>Benſon,</hi> and ſome of the Bench con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>James Nayler.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>AT the Seſſions of the peace holden at <hi>Appleby</hi> the 11 day of Ianuary 1652. upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:124878:31"/>
of <hi>James Nayler,</hi> it being alledged that the words by him ſpoken, were not within the Act againſt Blaſphemy, nor againſt any Law. It was replied by two of the Iuſtices, that rather then the ſaid <hi>James Nayler</hi> ſhould go at liberty, and abroad in the County, they would ſtand to the hazard of a fine to be impoſed upon them by the Iudges of the Aſſizes, or words to the ſame effect; and another of the Iuſtices ſaid openly, That they rather committed him upon the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters petition, (though no oath of the truth of any particular therein contained was made) then upon the Indictment, and upon making the Order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the people of Gods meeting peaceably in the night ſeaſon, it being urged that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had given liberty of meeting: it was repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that it was no matter, they would in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions reſtrain their meetings on the night time, or words the ſame in effect. Another Iuſtice who gave the charge, who was formerly in arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, the moſt part of his charge was compoſed of nothing elſe but railing againſt the people of God, whom by way of reproach he called Quakers: the truth of theſe particulars will be atteſted upon oath. Likewiſe Iuſtice <hi>Pearſon</hi> when I parted with him, told me, that he muſt give an account at <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and others, of their proceedings.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Jervis Benſon.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was ordered by the Justices at</hi> Apoleby, <hi>That</hi> Iames Nayler <hi>and</hi> Francis Howgill <hi>ſhould ſtay in priſon
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:124878:31"/>
till the petitions be anſwered, I was moved to anſwer them, and we could not have a Copy of the petitions from</hi> Tho. Kilner <hi>the Clerk of the Peace, but we muſt pay four ſhillings and ſix pence for them, which we know was oppreſsion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Prieſts Cruelty.</head>
               <p>THe chief Prieſts were ever the greateſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuters of the truth, and under the name of profeſſion, ſought always to deſtroy the ſeed of God where ever it was made manifeſt, and they are the ſame ſtill, vvhore ever the ſeed of God is raiſed up, then they in whom the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 3, 4, 5, 13.</note> is head, ſeek to devour it. The Dragon not having power to devour the man child, yet he wil ſtil peſecute the woman in vvhom he was brought forth. When Ieſus Chriſt vvas born, all Ieruſalem vvas moved and troubled, and vvhen <hi>Herod</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vvhere Chriſt ſhould be born, the chief <note place="margin">Mat. 2. 3, 4, 5, 16.</note> Prieſts and Scribes of the people told him, in <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem,</hi> and in all the coaſts thereof Ieſus Chriſt ſhewed to his Diſciples, that he was to ſuffer many things of the Elders and chief Prieſts, and <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 21</note> Scribes, and be killed of the chiefe Prieſts and <note place="margin">Mat. 21. 15.</note> Scribes: vvhen they ſaw the vvonderfull things that Jeſus Chriſt did, and that little children did confeſs him, they were ſore diſpleaſed, the chief Prieſts and Elders of the people came unto Chriſt and he was preaching, and asked, By what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity doſt thou theſe things, &amp; who gave thee that authority? The chief Prieſts and Phariſees ſought <note place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:124878:32"/>
to lay hands on Jeſus for ſpeaking the truth; Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus told his Diſciples, that he ſhould be betrayed into the hands of the chief Prieſts, and Scribes, and they would condemn him to death, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 18, 19. Mat. 26. 14, 15 57, 59, &amp;c.</note> him to the Gentiles to mock and to ſcourge, and to crucifie. The chief Prieſts, Scribes and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders aſſembled to the place of the higheſt Prieſts, and conſulted that they might take Ieſus by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, and kill him. The chief Prieſts hired <hi>Judas</hi> to betray Chriſt. The chief Prieſts and Elders of the people ſet a great multitud with ſwords and ſtaves to take Ieſus; and when he was taken, they led him to the high Prieſts, where the Scribes and Elders were aſſembled; the chief Prieſts and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and all the Councell ſought falſe witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain Ieſus to put him to death; The high Prieſt when he ſaw that he could not find witneſs to condemn him, then he aroſe, and provoke dhm to ſpeak, that he might enſnare him in his words; but when Ieſus held his peace, then the High Prieſt did adjure him by the living God, to tell whether he were the Son of God or no. And when he witneſſed forth the truth, the high Prieſt rent his cloaths, and ſaid, he hath ſpoken blaſphemy, what further need have we of witneſſes? And from that they concluded he was worthy of death, and then they ſpat in his face, and mocked him. And when the morning was come, all the chief Prieſts and Elders of the People took counſel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Mat. 27, 2.</note> Ieſus to put him to death: And when they had bound him they delivered him to <hi>Pilat.</hi> When <hi>Judas</hi> brought again the thirty pieces of ſilver, the chief Prieſts confeſſed it to be the price of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:124878:32"/>
blood, and took conſell how to diſpoſe of it. The <note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> chief Prieſts and Elders accuſed Chriſt before <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat</hi> of many things; <hi>Pilat</hi> knew that for envy they had delivered him. The chief Prieſts perſwaded <note place="margin">Verſ. 12, 13, 18. 41. 43</note> the people to take <hi>Barabbas,</hi> and deſtroy Ieſus. The The chief Prieſts mocked Ieſus on the croſs, with the Scribes and Elders, and ſaid, He truſted in <hi>God,</hi> let him deliverhim now if he wou'd have him; for he ſaid, I am the Son of God. The chief Prieſts called Chriſt a deceiver: The chiefe Prieſts and Elders deviſed a lie, and gave large mony to the <note place="margin">Mat. 28. 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> Soldiers to report it, and promiſed them ſecurity in ſo doing.</p>
               <p>The chief Prieſts and the Captain of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple come upon the Apoſtles, and being grieved <note place="margin">Acts 4. 1, 2, 3, 6, &amp;c.</note> that they preached through Ieſus the reſurrection of the dead, they laid hands on them, and put them in hold; and the next day the high Prieſt, and all his kindred gathered together, and when he had ſet them in the middeſt, they asked them by what vowes and by what means they had done this: and though they could not deny the power, yet they agreed to threaten the Apoſtles leſt they truth ſhould ſpread any further. The high Prieſt, and they that were with him, were filled with indignation, becauſe of the works done by the Apoſtles, and put them in the common Goal. The <note place="margin">Acts 17 18, 27, 28. 53.</note> high Pieſt called the Councel, and all the Senate of the children of Iſrael, againſt the Apoſtles, and ſent to the priſon, to have them brought; and when they were come, the high Prieſt ſaid, Did not we ſtrictly command you to teach no more in this name. And when the Apoſtles did ſtill witneſs
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:124878:33"/>
forth the truth, they took counſell to ſlay them. <note place="margin">Acts 7. 1. Acts 9. 1, 2, 21.</note> The High Prieſt examined <hi>Stephen,</hi> and for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing forth the truth, he was ſtoned to death. <hi>Saul</hi> had letters from the High Prieſt, whereby to perſecute the Saints, and to bring them bound ot the chief Prieſts. The High Prieſt commanded to ſmite <hi>Paul</hi> on the mouth for ſpeaking truth. Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">Acts 23. 2, 14. Acts 24. 2.</note> men having ſworn to murder <hi>Paul,</hi> came to the chief Prieſt for help to act it. The High Prieſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended with the Elders, and a certain Orator, who was to inform againſt <hi>Paul.</hi> The chief Prieſts <note place="margin">Acts 25. 15.</note> and Elders informed <hi>Feſtus,</hi> and deſired judgement againſt <hi>Paul.</hi> The Prieſts, and the Prophets, and <note place="margin">Ier. 26. 8. 11.</note> all the people ſaid, <hi>Jeremy</hi> thou ſhalt ſurely die, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſpoke the word of the Lord. The Prieſts <note place="margin">Ier. 23. 11.</note> and the Prophets accuſed <hi>Jeremy</hi> to the Princes, ſaying, This man is worthy of death; yea both Prieſt and Prophet are prophane, yea in my houſe I have found their wickedneſs, ſaith the Lord; yea his watchmen are all blind, they are ignorant, yea they are greedy Doggs, that can never have <note place="margin">Iſa. 56, 10, 11, 12.</note> enough, they are Shepeards that cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, they all look for their gain from their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Come ye, ſay they, I will fetch wine, and we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink, and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. Awake ye drunkards, and weep and howl all ye drinkers of wine, gird your ſelves and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Joel 1. 5, 13.</note> you Prieſts, howl you Miniſters of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, they build up Sion with blood, and Ieruſalem with iniquity, the Heads there of judge forre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <note place="margin">Micah 3. 10.</note> and the Prieſts thereof teach for hire, and the Prophets thereof divine for money, yet will
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:124878:33"/>
they lean upon the Lord, and ſay, is not the Lord amongſt us, no evil can come upon us: and now <note place="margin">Mic. 3. 10, 11.</note> ye Prieſts, this Commandment is for you, If ye will not hear, and if ye will not lay it to heart, to give glory unto my name, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 1, 2, 3, 4</note> I will even ſend a curſe upon you, and will curſe your bleſſings, yea, I have curſed them already becauſe you do not lay it to heart; but behold I will corrupt their ſeed, and ſpread dung upon their faces, even the dung of your ſolemn feaſts, and one ſhall take you away with it: And ye ſhall <note place="margin">Jer. 5. 30, 31.</note> know, that I have ſent this Commandment unto you, that my Covenant might be with <hi>Levi,</hi> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: A wonderful, a horrible thing is committed in the Land, the Prophets prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie falſly, and the Prieſts bear rule by their means, &amp; my people love to have it ſo, but what will you do in the end thereof: for from the leaſt of them to the greateſt of them, they are given to Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, and from the Prophet even unto the Prieſt, every one dealeth falſly: They have healed the hurt of the daughter of my people <note place="margin">Jer. 6. 13, 14, 15</note> deceitfully, ſaying, Peace, peace, when there is no peace: Were they aſhamed when they had committed abominations? nay they were not at all aſhamed, neither could they bluſh; therefore they ſhall fall amongſt them that fall, at the time that I viſit them, they ſhall be caſt down, ſaith the Lord.</p>
               <p>I was moved to write this, after the tryal at <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="afterword">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:124878:34"/>
               <head>An Exhortation to the People.</head>
               <p>FRiends, do not call this railing, becauſe we uſe plainneſs of ſpeech, and not with fained words, nor ſow pillows under your elbows, as the falſe Prophets did, as you read in the Scripture; but we uſe the ſame language of the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles, who ſpoke againſt fained humbleneſs, as it is as the Scripture ſaith, They go on in the way of Cain, and run greedily after the error of Balaam, and many ſhall follow their pernicious ways, of whom the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of: O all friends and people, ſee if there be not ſomething within you, which ſhews you ſin and evil, and the deceits of your own hearts; which if you do hearken to it, and love it, you will love Chriſt: for he is the light, and hating this light, you hate Chriſt, becauſe your deeds are evil, and will not bring your works to the light, leaſt the light ſhould reprove them: and here i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your condemnation, the light within you, and it is not a Chapter nor a Verſe without you: And loving this light, it will bring you off all the worlds ways and worſhips, to worſhip God: for they walked in their own ways, which ſpent their money for that which was not bread, and there you are in your own ways; and it will draw you out of all the worlds Churches, into the Church in God: and wait in this light, and it will gather all your hearts together, to live in unity one with another; and it will lead you to the everlaſting day of the Lord; and walking in that light, there
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124878:34"/>
will be no occaſion of ſtumbling: for being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient to the light, there will be ſtumbling at noon day: Therefore all people prize your time, this is the day of your viſitation and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and if ever you own a clean &amp; pure conſcience you will own us; and if ever you come to know Jeſus Chriſt, you will own us; and if ever you own the Lord God of heaven and earth, and come to know him, and worſhip him, you will then own us, and know us; and if ever you own the life of the Prophets and the Apoſtles, you will then own us to be ſent of God, and of God; and we ſeek not yours, but your ſaving health, and ſouls good, and your eternal peace and happineſs, and eternally ſhall you witneſs us, to that which doth convince you: I ſpeak that which will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with me in the end, when the thoughts of every mans heart ſhall be revealed, and the book of Conſcience ſhall be opened; therefore below in heart, and conſider where you are, and learn the leſſon of Chriſt, and put him on, and forſake all your blinde guides without you, and minde the guide within you; they are the ſons of God, that are guided by the Spirit of the Lord; they are not the Sons of God, who can profeſs and talk of the Letter, and perſecute them which are contrary to their opinions, but ſhew forth to be the children of the Devil, and not of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:124878:35"/>
MY name is covered from the world, and the world knows not me, nor my name; the earthly name the earthly man knows, and he is afraid of reproach, and cannot bear it upon the earthly name; he that overcometh, hath the new name, and knoweth it; he that is not come into the War, knows it not; he that overcometh, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his throne, he that overcometh is crowned, he that is judged, and judgement, is brought into victory, and then it is ſet in the earth; he that overcometh, eateth of the hidden Manna; he that overcometh, ſhal inherite all things: he that is without, hath the old name, and wants all things, and cannot judge any thing; for the natural man knows not the things of God, but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual man judgeth all things; he that hath an ear to hear, let him hear; and bleſſed is he that reads, and doth underſtand what he reads.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:124878:35"/>
               <head>TO THE Parliament of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and the General, and Major General of the ARMY.</head>
               <head type="sub">A Declaration of the preſent condition of ſeveral Inhabitants in <hi>Weſtmeriand,</hi> and ſome part in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> whoſe names are ſubſcribed, who have been faithful to the Parliament, and ſerviceable in their places to this Commonwealth, to the hazard of their Lives, Liberties and Eſtates.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Declareth,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Lord hath made known him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and manifeſted his love to us, in letting us ſee the deadneſs and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptineſs of all the outward Miniſtry of the world; and hath according to his own
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124878:36"/>
promiſe, led us forth of the barren Wilderneſs of outward carnal Worſhips, and is his him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf become out Teacher, and hath made us wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to wait alone upon him for Teaching: By the power and vertue of which, we deny all the Teaching which ſtands in the will of man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and ſo meeting together to wait upon the Lords unlimitted power, exhoring and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up one another in our moſt holy faith, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the practice of all the Saints before us; Not onely ſpending the Firſt day of the week in ſuch Exerciſes; but ſeveral other days and nights, as the Lord gives us opportunity, to the great refreſhment of our ſouls, and uniting of our hearts to the Lord, and one to another, to his everlaſting praiſe and glory; and having oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to praiſe the Lord for that Freedom which the Parliament doth allow us, for which the Prieſts much maligns us, and ſtirs up the ignorant people in their Publique Aſſemblies, to execute their rigour upon us, fomentinglyes, and accuſing us to the Magiſtrates falſely, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſome to be Endicted, ſome Impriſoned, and ſome bound over for no juſt cauſe at all: And hath done all that in them lies to deprive us of that Liberty which the Parliament hath afforded: As may appear, by ſeveral Orders made at a late Seſſions at Appleby in Weſtmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; wherein they have Ordered, That we ſhall not meet together in the night time, which hath been the practice of the Saints in former ages, and hath been our practice, becauſe there are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124878:36"/>
many Servants and young labouring people, which cannot come on the day, which comes at the night, becauſe we would not give an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of offence: Wherein we do witneſs, that while we did meet together on the night to ſport and ſpend the time in vanity, we were not medled withal; but now we do teſtifie againſt all ſuch practices: and who lives now in the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hates us: But Juſtice which cuts down fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, and gives way for truth to riſe, we own. But there are ſeveral got into Commiſſion of the peace, formerly Malignants, and ſome that have been actually in Arms againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, contrary to the Act of Parliament, and are utter Enemies to the Truth, as doth appear, not onely here, but likewiſe in Yorkſhire, where there hath been ten of our Brethren and Siſters kept in Priſon in York Caſtle, ſome of them the moſt part of a whole year, and ſince the laſt Aſſizes were kept in cloſe Priſon, until one of them dyed, and ſo continued in cloſe Priſon, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it pleaſed the Lord to move the hearts of ſome to procure them more Liberty. And whereas we are a people accuſed to deny Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, it is not ſo; For Juſtice we own in our ſouls, which cuts down corruption, which keeps the ſoul in the death; For let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher power: For all power is of God, and that we ſet up, own and honor for Conſcience ſake, and all men in the Lord. Likewiſe our dear Brother <hi>James Nayler</hi> lies in Priſon in Appleby, who ſerved the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:124878:37"/>
under the Command of Major General <hi>Lambert,</hi> betwixt eight and nine years, as we believe ſome of the Army can witneſs: All that we deſire is, that Books may be printed whereby the Truth may be manifeſted: And if we tranſgreſs or offend, we are willing to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</p>
               <argument>
                  <p>This Petition was ſigned by Three hundred and twenty nine of the Inhabitants of Lancaſhire, and part of Weſtmerland.</p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
